片名：马耳他之鹰/枭巢喋血战
1539年，马耳他圣殿骑士
向西班牙查理五世朝贡
送给他一只浑身上下
包裹着稀世珍宝的金鹰
但海盗拦截了
这艘载有无价之宝的船只
马耳他之鹰的命运至今仍是谜团
三藩市
金门大桥
怎样，小甜心？
-Yes, sweetheart? -There's a girl wants to see you.
有个叫旺德莉的女子来找你
Her name's Wonderly.
客户吗？
-Customer? -I guess so.
我想是吧，你会很想见她的 她是大美女
You'll want to see her, anyway. She's a knockout.
请她进来吧，爱菲，请她进来
Shoo her in, Effie, darling. Shoo her in.
请进，旺德莉小姐
EFFIE: Will you come in, Miss Wonderly?
谢谢
Thank you.
- 请坐，旺德莉小姐 - 谢谢
-Won't you sit down, Miss Wonderly? -Thank you.
我跟旅馆打听过可靠私家侦探的消息
I inquired at the hotel for the name of a private detective.
他们提到你的名字
They mentioned yours.
请从头跟我讲起吧
Suppose you tell me about it from the very beginning.
我是纽约人
-I'm from New York. -Uh-huh.
我在找我妹
I'm trying to find my sister.
我相信她人在三藩市这里
I have reason to believe that she's here...
跟一个名字叫佛洛德?德斯派的人在一起
...with a man by the name of Thursby. Floyd Thursby.
我不晓得他们是在哪认识的
I don't know where she met him.
我们一直不很亲近
We've never been as close as sisters ought to be.
如果亲近点，柯琳就会告诉我
If we had, perhaps Corinne would have told me
她计划和他私奔
she was planning on running away.
爸妈去了檀香山
Mother and Father are in Honolulu.
他们会急死的 我必须在我爸妈回来前找到她
I've got to find her before they get back.
他们下月一号回来
-They're coming home the first.
你收到过你妹的消息吗？
-You've had word of your sister?
两周前她给我写过一封信
A letter from her about two weeks ago.
她只说她没事，很好
It said nothing except that she was all right.
我曾发电报给她，求她回家
I sent her a telegram, begging her to come home.
我是寄到这里存局候领的 那是她唯一给我的地址
I sent it to General Delivery. That was the address she gave.
等了一个星期，还是没回音 所以就决定自己来看看
I waited a week and no answer came, so I decided to come out here myself.
我曾写信告诉她我会来 我不该那样，是吧？
I wrote her that I was coming. I shouldn't have done that, should I?
知道该做什么可没那么容易
It's not always easy to know what to do.
还是没找到？
You haven't found her?
没，我在信里要她在圣马克见面
No. I told her in my letter that I'd be at the St. Mark and for her to meet me there.
我等了三天，她没来 就连口信也没有
I waited three whole days. She didn't come, didn't even send a message.
等待是可怕的
It was horrible, waiting.
我又寄了封存局候领
I sent her another letter.
昨天下午，我去了邮局一趟
Yesterday afternoon, I went to the post office.
柯琳没有去拿她的信，但佛洛德去了
Corinne didn't call for her mail, but Floyd Thursby did.
他不告诉我柯琳在哪里
He wouldn't tell me where Corinne was.
他只说她不想见我
He said she didn't want to see me.
真不敢相信
I can't believe that.
他还答应如果她肯来，就今晚带她来旅馆
He promised to bring her to the hotel, if she'd come.
他说他知道她不肯来的 他应承说如果她不来，他自己也会来
He said he knew she wouldn't. He promised to come himself if she didn't. He--
抱歉
Oh, excuse me.
没事，进来吧，麦尔斯
Oh, it's all right, Miles. Come in.
旺德莉小姐，这位是我搭档，麦尔斯?阿契尔
Miss Wonderly, my partner, Miles Archer.
旺德莉小姐的妹妹从纽约家里逃出来
Miss Wonderly's sister ran away...
跟一个名叫佛洛德?德斯派的家伙跑了
...with a fellow named Floyd Thursby.
他们目前人在三藩市这里
They're here in San Francisco.
旺德莉小姐见过德斯派，约好今晚碰面
Miss Wonderly has seen Thursby, has a date to meet him.
他也许会带她妹去，极有可能他不会
Maybe he'll bring the sister with him. Chances are he won't.
她要我们帮她找妹妹，带她回家
Miss Wonderly wants us to find the sister, get her away from him and back home.
- 是吧？- 是
-Right? -Yes.
很简单，今晚找个人去旅馆
Now, it's simply a matter of having a man at the hotel this evening...
跟着他到你妹妹那里
...to shadow him when he leads us to your sister.
如果她还是不想离开他
If, after we've found her, she still doesn't want to leave him....
- 我们自有办法 - 没错
-Well, we have ways of managing that. -Yeah.
但请小心
But you must be careful.
我很怕他，怕他做出什么事
I'm deathly afraid of him, of what he might do.
她这么年轻，他把她从纽约 带到这里是很严重的…
She's so young. His bringing her here is a serious--
他不会对她做什么吗？
Mightn't he do something to her?
别担心，我们会处理的
Leave that to us. We'll know how to handle him.
但他这个人很危险
But I want you to know he's a dangerous man.
我真的认为他这个人什么都干得出来
I honestly don't think he'd stop at anything.
他会毫不犹豫杀死柯琳自救
I don't think he'd hesitate to kill Corinne if he thought it would save him.
他会不会用和她结婚来掩饰？
Could he cover up by marrying her?
他在英国有妻小
He has a wife and three children in England.
他们常常住英国，但不尽然 形容一下他吧
They usually do, though not always in England. What's he look like?
他的头发很黑，眉毛很浓密
He has dark hair and thick, bushy eyebrows.
讲话音量很大
He talks in a loud, blustery manner.
看起来就很暴力的样子
He gives the impression of being violent.
今天早上他穿了一套灰色行头
He was wearing a light gray suit and a gray hat when I saw him this morning.
- 他是干哪一行的？ - 不晓得
-What does he do for a living? -I haven't the faintest idea.
- 你们约几点见面？ - 八点以后
-What time's he coming to see you? -After 8:00.
好的，旺德莉小姐，我们会派人过去
All right, Miss Wonderly. We'll have a man there.
我亲自出马
I'll look after it myself.
谢谢
Oh, thank you.
对了…
Oh, yes.
够吗？
Will that be enough?
- 谢谢 - 不客气
-Thank you. -Not at all.
如果你跟德斯派在大厅碰面会有所帮助的
It'll help some if you meet Thursby in the lobby.
- 我会的- 到时别找我
-I will. -You don't have to look for me.
- 我会暗中保护你的- 谢谢
-I'll see you all right. -Thank you.
- 非常感激 - 再见
-Thank you so much. -Goodbye.
真金白银
They're right enough.
我看她包里还不少
They have brothers in her bag.
- 你觉得她怎样？- 很可爱
-What do you think of her? -Oh, she's sweet.
也许是你先看到她的 山姆，但是我先开口的
Maybe you saw her first, Sam, but I spoke first.
你还真会动脑筋
You've got brains.
没错，是这样的
Yes, you have.
史派德和阿契尔事务所
布什街
喂？
SPADE:Hello?
对，请讲
Yeah. Speaking.
麦尔斯?阿契尔死了？
Miles Archer dead?
哪里？
Where?
斯托克顿布什街
Bush and Stockton?
好的
Yeah.
15分钟赶到
In 15 minutes.
谢谢
Thanks.
爱菲吗？
Hello, Effie?
是我！
It's me.
听我讲，宝贝
Now, listen, precious.
麦尔斯被枪杀了
Miles has been shot. [EFFIE SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
对…死了
Yeah. Dead.
别激动
Now, don't get excited.
对…
Yeah.
你负责告诉伊娃这个噩耗，我先行动
Now, you'll have to break the news to Iva. I'd fry first.
不要告诉她我的行踪
And keep her away from me.
这样才乖嘛
That's a good girl.
赶快过去
Now get right over there.
你简直是太好了
You're an angel.
再见
Bye.
- 你想干嘛？- 我叫山姆?史派特，汤姆?柏郝斯打过电话给我
-What do you want here? -I'm Sam Spade. Tom Polhaus phoned.
我刚刚还认不出你他们在后面
Oh, I didn't know you at first. They're back there.
你好，山姆，我想在我们带走他前，你会想看看
POLHAUS: Hello, Sam. I figured you'd want to see it before we took him away.
谢谢，汤姆，怎么回事？
-Well, thanks, Tom. What happened?
被这把威布利
-Got him right through the pump with this.
枪杀的
It's a Webley.
英制品，对吧？
English, ain't it?
对，威布利福斯裴利点45自动手枪，8发，绝版了
Yeah. A Webley-Fosbery .45 automatic, eight shot. They don't make them anymore.
- 开了几枪？- 一枪
-How many gone out of it? -Just one.
往这里开，对吧？
SPADE:Let's see. Shot up here, huh?
就跟你一样这样站着，背对着围栏
Standing like you are, with his back to the fence.
开枪的人站在这里
The man who shot him stood here.
他后仰翻过围栏
He went over, taking the top of the fence.
掉下山，被那块石头接住，对吧？
Went on down the hill and got caught on that rock.
枪爆烧到他的外套
That's it. The blast burnt his coat.
- 是谁发现的？ - 巡逻的人
-Who found him? -Man on the beat.
- 还有没有别人听到枪声？- 一定有，我们刚到
-Anybody hear the shot? -Somebody must've. We just got here.
在我带走他以前，你还想看看他吗？
You want to go down and have a look at him?
不了，该看的你都看到了
No, you've seen everything I could.
他的枪还插在身后没开过
His gun was tucked away. Hadn't been fired.
他的外套扣着
His overcoat was buttoned.
我在他的背心口袋里找到一张百元钞票，裤袋里还有三十几块
I found a $100 bill in his vest pocket and 30-some bucks in his pants.
他在执行任务，是吧，山姆？
Was he working, Sam?
怎样？
Well?
- 对，他在跟踪一个名叫德斯派的家伙 - 干嘛？
-Yeah, he was tailing a guy named Thursby. -What for?
干嘛？
What for?
想知道他住哪里，别盘问我了，汤姆
He wanted to find out where he lived. Don't crowd me, Tom.
我要去通知麦尔斯的太太噩耗了
I'm going on down and break the news to Miles' wife.
一定很为难吧？他死得那么惨
It's tough, him getting it like that, ain't it?
麦尔斯自己也有错，就像我们所有人
Miles had his faults, like any of us...
但我想他的优点也不少
...but I guess he must've had some good points too, huh?
我想是吧
I guess so.
请找旺德莉小姐
Miss Wonderly, please.
退房了吗？几点？
Uh? Checked out? What time?
有没有留回信地址？
Any forwarding address?
谢谢
Thanks.
你好，汤姆，你好啊，警探，请进
SPADE: Oh, hello, Tom. Hello, lieutenant. Come in.
请坐
Sit down.
想喝什么？
Drink?
你跟麦尔斯的太太讲过了吗？
Did you break the news to Miles' wife, Sam?
她承受得了吗？
-Uh-huh. -How'd she take it?
- 我不了解女人 - 从何时开始？
-I don't know anything about women. -Since when?
你配什么枪？
-What kind of a gun do you carry?
没，我不喜欢枪，当然办公室里有几把
-None. I don't like them. -Course, there are some at the office.
这里没有吗？你确定？
-You don't have one here?
到处看啊 可以把垃圾桶翻个底朝天啊
-You sure about that? -Look around. Turn the dump upside down.
如果你有搜查令的话，我不会抗议的
I won't squawk, if you got a search warrant.
我们不想搞出…
-We don't wanna-- -What are you birds sucking around for?
我不喜欢这样！你们来究竟为什么，直说，要不走人
Tell me or get out.
你不能这样待我们 山姆，我们有公务在身
You can't treat us like that. It ain't right. We got our work to do.
你干嘛跟踪德斯派？
Why were you tailing Thursby?
我没有，麦尔斯在跟 原因很简单，我们的客户…
Miles was, and for the simple reason we had a lient--
- 谁？- 这一点我不能讲
-Who's the client? -Sorry, I can't tell you that.
拜托，山姆，说吧，你查到什么线索
Be reasonable, Sam. Give us a break, will you?
要不我们怎么查麦尔斯被杀的案子
How we gonna turn up anything if you don't tell us what you got?
汤姆说，你匆忙得
Tom says you were in too much of a hurry
看都不看一眼死去的搭档
to stop and look at your dead partner.
你也没去阿契尔的家和他太太讲
And you didn't go to Archer's house to tell his wife.
我们打过电话去你办公室 那个女孩说，是你要她那样做的
We called your office and the girl there said you told her to do it.
我给你十分钟打电话给那个女孩
I'll give you 10 minutes to get a phone and do your talking to the girl.
给你十分钟联络德斯派的住所
I'll give you 10 minutes to get to Thursby's. Geary and Leavenworth.
GL那里，你轻而易举可以做到的
-You could do it easily.
你男朋友说什么啊，汤姆？
-What's your boyfriend getting at, Tom?
德斯派在他的旅馆外被枪击了
Just this, Thursby was shot down in front of his hotel...
你离开布什街半小时后
...about a half an hour after you left Bush Street.
把你的爪子拿开
-Keep your paws off me.
你到家时几点？
-What time did you get home?
比你早到就是了，我闲逛了一下想事情
Just a few minutes ahead of you. I was walking around, thinking.
我们知道你去了那里，我们在电话上找过你
We know you weren't here. Where did you walk to?
- 你去了哪里？- 布什街
-Up Bush Street. -You see anybody--?
- 你看到什么人…- 不，没有目击证人
SPADE: No. No witnesses.
我知道自己的处境了
Well, I know where I stand, now.
抱歉我站起来了，伙计们
Sorry I got up on my hind legs,
但你们想吊死我，让我很紧张
but you fellas trying to rope me made me nervous.
麦尔斯的死本来就让我心烦意乱 你们又来搅局
Miles getting bumped off upset me, and then you birds cracking foxy.
但没事，我现在了解情况了
It's all right, now I know what it's all about.
算了，山姆
Forget it, Sam.
德斯派死了？
-Thursby die? -Yeah.
我是怎么干掉德斯派的？我忘了
How'd I kill him? I forget.
他背后中四枪，点44或点45手枪 街对面开的枪
He was shot in the back four times with a .44 or .45 from across the street.
没人看到，但看得出来是这样
Nobody saw it, but that's how it figures.
旅馆服务员知道他什么吗？
-Hotel people know anything?
没什么，就知道他在那里住了一周
-Nothing, except that he lived there a week.
- 一个人？- 对，一个人
-Alone? -Yeah, alone.
他是什么人？他搞什么把戏？
Did you find out who he was? What his game was? Well, did you?
- 我们以为你知道- 我从没见过德斯派，不管死的活的
-We thought you could tell us that. -I've never seen Thursby, dead or alive.
你了解我的，史派德
Well, you know me, Spade.
不管是不是你干的
If you did it, or if you didn't...
我还是会和你公平交易，提供给你线索
...you'll get a square deal and most of the breaks.
我不会怪你，别人干掉了你的搭档…
Don't know as I'd blame you much. The man that killed your partner.
但我还是会盯着你
But that won't stop me from nailing you.
很公平
Fair enough.
但你们和我喝一杯我会感觉好点
But I'd feel better about it if you'd have a drink with me.
祝成功破案
Success to crime.
德斯派，阿契尔谋杀案并案
私家侦探在跟踪德斯派
她在里面
EFFIE: She's in there.
- 我让你帮我挡她的 - 你没教我方法嘛
I told you to keep her away from me. Yes, but you didn't tell me how.
别对我发脾气，山姆，我受了她一整晚
Oh, don't be cranky with me, Sam. I've had her all night.
抱歉，亲爱的，我不是想…
Sorry, angel. I didn't mean--
你好，伊娃
Hello, Iva.
山姆…
Oh, Sam.
亲爱的
Darling.
爱菲都处理得很好吧？
Effie take care of everything?
我想是吧
I think so.
山姆，是你杀的他吗？
Sam, did you kill him?
是谁这样跟你讲的啊？
Who put that bright idea in your head?
我还记得你说过 要不是为了麦尔斯，你已经…
Well, I thought you said if it wasn't for Miles, you'd....
对我好点，山姆
Be kind to me, Sam.
你杀了我丈夫，山姆…对我好点！
"You killed my husband, Sam. Be kind to me."
不要，伊娃，不要！
Don't, Iva. Don't.
你不该来这里的，你必须待在家里
You shouldn't have come here today, darling. You ought to be home.
你会很快到，是吧？
You'll come soon?
尽快就是了
Soon as I can.
再见，伊娃
Goodbye, Iva.
怎样
EFFIE: Well?
你跟那个寡妇搞得怎样？
How did you and the widow make out?
她以为麦尔斯是我干掉的
-She thinks I shot Miles.
- 这样你就可以娶她了？ - 条子以为德斯派是我干掉的
-So you could marry her?The cops think I killed Thursby,
那个麦尔斯帮旺德莉女士跟踪的家伙
the guy Miles was tailing for that Wonderly dame.
你觉得我干掉谁啦？
Who do you think I shot?
你会娶伊娃吗？
Are you going to marry Iva?
别傻了，真希望我从没看到过她
Don't be silly. I wish I'd never laid eyes on her.
她会不会干掉他啊？
Do you suppose she could have killed him?
真有你的，简直就是笨得可爱
You're an angel. A nice, rattlebrained little angel.
- 是吗？ - 谢谢，甜心
-Oh, am I? -Thanks, honey.
如果我告诉你你的伊娃没回家多久
Suppose I told you Iva hadn't been home many minutes...
当我凌晨3点给她带去噩耗时…？
...when I arrived to break the news at 3:00 this morning?
你会告诉我吗？
Are you telling me?
她脱衣服时要我在门边等她
She kept me waiting while she undressed.
她的衣帽，内衣扔在椅子上
Her clothes were on a chair where she'd dumped them, hat and coat underneath.
她的内衣还是温的咧！
Her slip, on top, was still warm.
她弄皱了床，但皱纹也没压扁
She'd wrinkled the bed, but the wrinkles weren't mashed down.
你真有侦探的料，但不是她干的，亲爱的
You're a detective, darling, but she didn't kill him.
条子真以为那个谁是你干掉的吗？
Do the police really think you shot this what's-his-name?
看着我，山姆
Do they? Look at me, Sam.
我很担心你
You worry me.
你总以为一切尽在掌握
You think you know what you're doing,
你太精于为自己打算
but you're too slick for your own good.
你有天会发现的 史派特和阿契尔事务所
Someday you're going to find it out. Spade and Archer.
旺德莉小姐
Oh, yes, Miss Wonderly.
喂…
Hello?
是，我是山姆?史派特
Yeah, this is Sam Spade.
哪里？
Where?
加利福尼亚巷柯罗纳特公寓，1001室
Coronet Apartments, California Avenue, apartment 1001.
叫什么名？李白朗小姐
What's the name? Miss LeBlanc.
我马上过来
Okay, I'll be right over.
把麦尔斯的桌子搬出办公室
Oh, have Miles' desk moved out of the office...
换掉门上和窗上的 “史派特和阿契尔”字样
...and have "Spade and Archer" taken off all the doors and windows...
改成“山姆?史派特”
...and have "Samuel Spade" put on.
进来吧，史派特先生
Oh, come in, Mr. Spade.
一团乱，都还没整理好，请坐
Everything's upside down. I haven't finished unpacking. Sit down.
史派特先生，我…
Mr. Spade, I....
我必须要跟你忏悔
I have a terrible, terrible confession to make.
我昨天跟你讲的那一切…
That story I told you yesterday...
是捏造的
...was just a story.
我们也没太相信…小姐…
Oh, that. Well, we didn't exactly believe your story, Miss....
你名叫旺德莉还是李白朗？
What is your name, Wonderly or LeBlanc?
说真的，是奥夏克尼希 布瑞怡特?奥夏克尼希
It's really O'Shaughnessy. Brigid O'Shaughnessy.
我们没相信你讲的那些 布瑞怡特?奥夏克尼希
We didn't believe your story, Miss O'Shaughnessy.
- 我们只是相信你的两百块 - 你是指…
-We believed your $200. -You mean that....
如果你讲的是实话，就不会付这么多钱
You paid us more than if you'd been telling the truth...
付得太多了
...and enough more to make it all right.
史派德，昨晚的事怪我吗？
Tell me, Mr. Spade, am I to blame for last night?
你警告过我们德斯派是危险人物
You warned us that Thursby was dangerous.
关于你妹的事，你撒了谎
Of course, you lied to us about your sister,
但那不算，我们没上当
but we didn't believe you.
不，我不会说是你的错
No, I wouldn't say that you were at fault.
谢谢
Thank you.
阿契尔先生昨天还活生生的
Mr. Archer was so alive yesterday...
- 如此立体和亲切…- 够了
-...so solid and hearty, and-- -Stop it.
他很清楚出来混，迟早要还的
He knew what he was doing. Those are the chances we take.
他成家了没？
Was he married?
他保了1万块的险，膝下无子 一个不喜欢他的太太
Yeah, with 10,000 insurance, no children and a wife that didn't like him.
- 请别…- 本来就是这样
-Please don't. -That's the way it was.
现在没时间去担心那个了
Anyway, there's no time for worrying about that now.
外面有一大群警察和副地方检察官…
Out there's a flock of policemen and assistant district attorneys...
出动，鼻子在地上嗅
...running around with their noses to the ground.
他们知道我吗？
Mr. Spade, do they know about me?
还不知道，见到你以前我一直在敷衍他们
Not yet. I've been stalling them until I could see you.
他们非得知道不可吗？
Do they have to know?
你就不能隐瞒我吗？这样我就不会被盘问
Can't you shield me so I won't have to answer their questions?
如果我知道真相的话 也许还做得到
Maybe, but I gotta know what it's all about.
我不能告诉你
I can't tell you.
现在不能告诉你
I can't tell you now.
等到可以时，我会跟你讲的
I will later, when I can.
请你信任我，史派特先生
You've got to trust me, Mr. Spade.
我很孤单和害怕
Oh, I'm so alone and afraid.
如果你不帮我的话，就没人能帮我了
I've got nobody to help me if you won't help me.
请你慷慨一点吧，史派特先生
Be generous, Mr. Spade.
你很勇敢，还很坚强
You're brave. You're strong.
你可以给我些勇气和力量，我肯定
You can spare me some of that courage and strength, surely.
帮我，我真的很需要你的帮忙
Help me, Mr. Spade. I need help so badly.
我没权力求你，但我还是求了
I have no right to ask you. I know I haven't, but I do ask you.
帮我
Help me.
你不需要什么帮忙，你很厉害了
You won't need much of anybody's help. You're good.
都是你的眼神，还有你那悸动的声音
It's chiefly your eyes, I think, and that throb you get in your voice...
你说“请你慷慨一点吧，史派特先生”时
...when you say things like, "Be generous, Mr. Spade."
我活该
I deserve that.
我讲话方式挺虚假的 但我讲的事是真的
But the lie was in the way I said it, not at all in what I said.
如果你不信任我的话，都是我的错
It's my own fault if you can't believe me now.
你现在变得很危险哦
Now you are dangerous.
我恐怕帮不上你的忙
But I'm not going to be able to be of much help to you...
除非我知道真相
...unless I've got some idea what it's all about.
我需要你那佛洛德?德斯派的一些线索
For instance, I've gotta have some sort of a line on your Floyd Thursby.
我们是在东方认识的
I met him in the Orient.
上个礼拜我们从香港飞到这里 他本来答应要帮我的
We came here from Hong Kong last week. He promised to help me.
但他却利用我的无依无靠背叛了我
He took advantage of my dependence to betray me.
背叛你？那你为什么还找人跟踪他？
Betray you? How? Why did you want him shadowed?
这样我才能了解他到了 哪一步，在见谁
I wanted to find out how far he'd gone, whom he was meeting, things like that.
- 阿尔契是他杀的吗？- 肯定
-Did he kill Archer? -Certainly.
他有一把鲁格尔手枪 阿契尔不是被鲁格尔枪杀的
He had a Luger in his shoulder holster. Archer wasn't shot with a Luger.
你不会是以为是我干的吧？！
Mr. Spade, you don't think I had anything to do with the death of Mr. Archer?
- 是你吗？- 当然不是！
-Did you? -No.
很好
That's good.
佛洛德常会多带一把左轮手枪在外套口袋
Floyd always carried an extra revolver in his overcoat pocket.
干嘛老带枪？
Why all the guns?
他是靠枪吃饭
He lived by them.
他第一次去香港时，就是当一个
The story is that he first came to the Orient...
不得不离开美国的赌客的保镖的
...as bodyguard to a gambler who'd had to leave the States.
赌客从此失踪，佛洛知道了…
The gambler had disappeared. Floyd knew about the disappearance.
我不晓得
I don't know.
我只知道总会全副武装，他睡觉时
I do know he always went heavily armed, and that he never went to sleep...
床周围地板上总是铺着弄皱的报纸
...without covering the floor around his bed with crumpled newspapers...
这样就没人能静悄悄的走进他的房间
...so that nobody could come silently into his room.
你挑了一个不错的玩伴哦
You picked a nice sort of a playmate.
他本来是能帮上我的忙的，如果他够忠诚
Only that sort could have helped me, if he'd been loyal.
- 你的情况有多糟？- 要多糟有多糟
-How bad a spot are you actually in? -Bad as could be.
生命有危险？
Physical danger?
我可不是什么英雄，死最糟了
I'm not heroic. I don't think there's anything worse than death.
- 就这样了？- 就这样了，真的和我们就坐在这里一样
-Then it's that? -It's that, as surely as we're sitting here.
除非你帮我
Unless you help me.
德斯派是谁杀的？是你的还是他的敌人？
Who killed Thursby, your enemies or his?
不晓得…
I don't know.
我想是他的敌人
His, I suppose.
我很害怕，不晓得
I'm afraid. I don't know.
根本无望，我不晓得你想怎样
This is hopeless. I don't know what you want done.
甚至不晓得你知不知道要怎样
-I don't even know if you know.
你不会去报警吧？
-You won't go to the police?
报警？我只要站直了他们就会蜂拥而至
Go to them? All I gotta do is stand still, they'll be all over me.
好啦，我会告诉他们我知道的 你必须冒险
I'll tell them all I know, and you'll take your chances.
你很有耐性，你想帮我
You've been patient with me. You've tried to help me.
没用的吧，我想
It's useless and hopeless, I suppose.
谢谢你，我会冒自己的险的
I do thank you for what you've done. I'll have to take my chances.
- 你有多少钱？- 我剩下5百块
How much money have you got? I've got about $500 left.
给我
Give it to me.
- 这里只有4百块 - 我还得生活
-There's only $400 here. -I had to keep some to live on.
- 筹得到钱吗？- 不行
-Well, can't you get some more? -No.
没东西可换钱吗？
Got anything you can raise some money on?
- 我有貂皮大衣和珠宝 - 当掉
-I've got some furs and a little jewelry. -You'll have to hock them.
给你
There you are.
我马上回来，带最好的消息给你
I'll be back as soon as I can with the best news I can manage.
我会按四声门铃… 长…短…长…短…
I'll ring four times. Long, short, long, short.
你不用去开门，我自己会进来
And no, you needn't bother to come to the door. I'll let myself in.
有好消息吗？
Anything stirring?
花是你送来的吗？
Did you send the flowers?
你真是无价之宝，亲爱的 帮我接律师，好吗？
You're invaluable, darling. Say, get my lawyer on the phone, will you?
喂，锡德？
Hello, Sid?
我要让一个验尸官去死了
I think I'm going to have to tell a coroner to go to blazes, Sid.
我可不可以像牧师或律师那样
Can I hide behind the sanctity of my client's identity...
保留客户的神圣秘密？
...secrets and what-nots all the same, priest or lawyer?
我知道，但邓迪变得有点粗暴
Yeah, but Dundy's getting rambunctious
这次有点过分
and maybe it is a bit thick this time.
站在安全这一边要付出多少代价？
Yeah. What'll it cost to be on the safe side?
好吧，也许值得，就这么办
Well, maybe it's worth it. Okay, go ahead.
栀子花
Gardenia.
快，亲爱的，带他进来
Quick, darling, in with him.
进来吧，开罗先生
Will you come in, Mr. Cairo?
请坐，开罗先生
Will you sit down, Mr. Cairo?
谢谢
Thank you, sir.
有何贵干，开罗先生？
Now, what can I do for you, Mr. Cairo?
身为一名陌生人 我可不可以向你搭档的意外致哀？
May a stranger offer condolences for your partner's unfortunate death?
谢谢
Thanks.
情况正如报纸暗示的
Is there, Mr. Spade, as the newspapers imply...
那件不幸事件
...a certain relationship between that unfortunate happening...
真的跟稍后德斯派的死有关吗？
...and the death a little later of the man Thursby?
很抱歉，无关！
I beg your pardon. No.
我不是闲得无聊问这个问题的
More than idle curiosity prompted my question.
这样讲好了，史派特先生，我在找
See, Mr. Spade, I'm trying to recover...
一件饰品，就说它遗失了好了
...an ornament that, shall we say, has been mislaid.
我想…也希望你能帮我
-Uh-huh. -I thought and hoped you could assist me.
那件饰品是一尊雕像
The ornament is a statuette.
一只黑鸟
A black figure of a bird.
我谨代表物主
I am prepared to pay, on behalf of the figure's rightful owner...
打算高价找回它，酬劳是5千块
...the sum of $5,000 for its recovery.
我答应…那句话是怎么讲的？
I am prepared to promise that-- What is the phrase?
不问任何问题
No questions will be asked.
5千块不算少
$5,000 is a lot of money.
什么，爱菲
Yes, Effie?
不，行了，出去时候锁好门就行
No, that'll be all. Just be sure to lock the door behind you on your way out.
晚安
Good night.
5千块很…
$5,000 is--
手放在脖子后面
Clasp your hands together at the back of your neck.
我要搜你的办公室，史派特先生
I intend to search your offices, Mr. Spade.
我警告你哦 如果你想阻止我，我会开枪哦
I warn you, if you attempt to prevent me, I shall certainly shoot you.
搜吧
Go ahead and search.
麻烦你到中间来一下
Will you please come to the center of the room?
我要确定你没配枪
Well, I have to make certain that you are not armed.
护照：乔伊?开罗
法国护照
你看看你，把我衣服搞成这样
Look what you did to my shirt.
很抱歉
Sorry.
但请你想一下 我发现5千块是骗人的时候
But imagine my embarrassment when I found out that $5,000 offer...
我多狼狈啊
-...was just hooey.
我讲的是真的
-Mr. Spade, my offer is genuine.
我会付你5千块，如果找得到它
I am prepared to pay $5,000 for the figure's return.
- 在你手上吗？- 没
-Do you have it? -No.
如果没有的话
But if it isn't here...
干嘛还要冒受伤的险阻止我搜查
...why did you risk injury to prevent my searching for it?
我能让别人随便在我这里撒野吗？
Why should I sit around here and let people come in and stick me up?
如果可以的话，帮物主省点钱
But certainly it is only natural that I try to save the owner...
是很自然的一件事
...such a considerable expense, if possible.
谁？
Who is he?
很抱歉，我不能回答你这个问题
Mr. Spade, you'll forgive my not answering that question.
我们最好看看
Well, I think we'd be better off all around
大家的牌是不是都在桌子上
if we'd put our cards on the table.
最好不要
No, I do not think it would be better.
这样讲好了，如果你知道的比我还多
You see, Mr. Spade, if you know more than I do...
我会因此而得利
...then I shall profit by your knowledge.
所以，就到5千块的程度吧
So will you, to the extent of $5,000.
好像没看到5千块啊
Well, there's nothing like $5,000 here.
原来你希望我的诚恳要有某程度的保证
Oh, you want some assurance of my sincerity?
- 一点聘金？怎么样？- 可以
-A retainer? Would that do? -It might.
你就先拿…1百块，怎样？
You will take, say, $100?
不…我要…两百块
No. I will take, say, $200.
你的第一个猜测是那只鸟在我手上
Let's see, your first guess was that I had the bird.
答案是不在我手上
There's nothing to that.
你的第二个猜测是什么？
What's your second guess?
你知道在哪里或者至少拿回来的方法
That you know where it is, or at least you know it is where you can get it.
你不是请我来杀人越货
You're not hiring me to do any murders or burglaries...
而是在合法的情况下把它找回来的
...but simply to get it back if possible, in an honest, lawful way?
如果可以的话当然最好
If possible.
但你自己决定就好
But in any case, with discretion.
如果你想联络我的话 我住在了望楼旅馆
When you wish to contact me, sir, I'm staying at the Hotel Belvedere.
635室
Room 635.
我诚恳希望能合作愉快
I sincerely expect the greatest mutual benefit...
互惠互利，史派特先生
...from our association, Mr. Spade.
枪可以还我了吧？
Oh, may I please have my gun, now?
当然，我全忘光了
Oh, sure. I'd forgotten all about it.
请你把手放在脖子后面
Will you please clasp your hands together at the back of your neck?
我要搜你的办公室
I intend to search your offices.
要不，我会…
Well, I'll be.
好啊…搜吧…
Why, sure.
我不会阻止你
Go ahead. I won't stop you.
右转，开上山，司机
-Turn to the right and go up the hill, driver. -Okay.
史派特先生
Mr. Spade.
你有没有什么消息？
Do you bring any news?
你有没有搞定，让警方不知道我？
Did you manage it so that the police won't have to know about me?
一段时间内他们是不会知道的
Well, they won't for a while, anyway.
你太棒了
You are wonderful.
你不会有麻烦吧？
You won't get into any trouble, will you?
某个程度内的麻烦也不错
SPADE: I don't mind a reasonable amount of trouble.
请坐
Do sit down.
你
You, uh....
你不是你假装的那种人
You aren't exactly the sort of a person you pretend to be, are you?
我不大明白你的意思
Why, I'm not sure I know exactly what you mean.
小女生的态度，你知道的 忸怩、吞吞吐吐什么的
The schoolgirl manner. You know, blushing, stammering and all that.
我没过过好生活，我过得很糟
I haven't lived a good life. I've been bad.
比你想像的还要糟
Worse than you could know.
很好，因为如果你真的就像自己装的
That's good, because if you actually were as innocent as you pretend to be...
那么无辜的话 我们就不会有什么发展
...we'd never get anywhere.
我不会再扮天真了
I won't be innocent.
很好
Good.
对了，今晚我见过乔伊?开罗
Oh, by the way, I saw Joel Cairo tonight.
- 你认识他吗？ - 点头之交
-Do you know him? -Only slightly.
你行啊，真行
You're good. You're very good.
- 他怎么说？- 说什么？
-What did he say? -About what?
- 说我 - 没什么
-About me. -Nothing.
- 那你们说什么了？- 他想付我5千块找回那只黑鸟
-What did you talk about then? -He offered me $5,000 for the black bird.
你不会是又想去走过去
You're not gonna go around straightening things
拨火吧？
and poking the fire again, are you?
当然不是
No, I'm not.
- 你怎么说？- 我说5千块不算少
-What did you say? -I said $5,000 was a lot of money.
那是
It is.
比我付你的还多 如果我得争取你的忠诚的话
It's more than I can ever offer you if I have to bid for your loyalty.
你说得很好
That's good coming from you.
除了钱外，你还给了我什么？
What have you ever given me beside money?
你给过我信任和真相吗？
You ever given me any of your confidence, any of the truth?
你不就是用钱来买我的忠诚吗？
Haven't you tried to buy my loyalty with money and nothing else?
我还有什么能付出的？
What else is there I can buy you with?
我不管你的秘密是什么
I don't care what your secrets are...
但如果我对你没有更多信心就不行
...but I can't go ahead without more confidence in you than I've got now.
你得说服我是怎么回事
You've got to convince me that you aren't fiddling around...
你不是在瞎混，等着天上掉馅饼
...hoping it'll all come out right in the end.
你就不能再信任我久点吗？
-Can't you trust me a little longer?
久点是多久？你还在等什么呢？
-What are you waiting for?
我必须找乔伊?开罗谈
I've got to talk to Joel Cairo.
今晚你可以去找他 他会去看戏，很快要停演了
You can see him tonight. He's at the theater. It'll be out soon.
- 我会在他的旅馆里留言 - 他不能来这里
-I'll leave a message at his hotel. -He can't come here.
我不能让他知道我在哪里
I can't let him know where I am. I'm afraid.
那就去我那里好了
My place, then.
喂？
Hello?
- 我想留言给乔伊?开罗 - 好的
-I want to leave a message for Joel Cairo. -All right.
如果我无法完全信任你
I never would've placed myself in this position
我就不会让自己处于这个境地
if I didn't trust you completely.
又来了？
That again?
这是真的
Do you know that's true, though?
你不必这么辛苦，设法说服我信任你
You don't have to trust me, so long as you can persuade me to trust you.
不必再担心这件事了
But don't worry about that now.
他随时会到
He'll be along any minute.
解决掉你跟开罗的事 然后我们的情况就会明朗
You get your business with Cairo over with, then we'll see how we stand.
你会让我用自己的方法处理他？
And you'll let me go about it with him in my own way?
当然
SPADE:
Oh, sure.
你简直就是上帝的恩赐
You are a godsend.
不要做得太过火
Well, now don't overdo it.
史派特先生，外面有人在监视
Mr. Spade, there is a boy outside. He seems to be watching the house.
我知道，我看到了
Yeah, I know. I spotted him.
怎样？什么监不监视的？
What? What's that? What boy?
有个年青人一直在跟踪我
I don't know. A kid. He's been trailing me all evening.
- 他有没有一直跟踪你到我公寓？- 我早把他甩掉了
-Did he follow you to my apartment? -I shook him long before that.
进来吧，开罗先生
Come in, Mr. Cairo.
- 很高兴再见到你，夫人 - 我想你也是
-I'm delighted to see you again, madam. -I was sure you would be, Joel.
史派特先生跟我提过你关于鹰的提议
Mr. Spade told me about your offer for the falcon.
- 钱你多快能筹得到？- 钱已经准备好了
-How soon can you have the money? -The money is ready.
- 现金？- 是的
O'SHAUGHNESSY: In cash? -Oh, yes.
你真的愿意付5千块找回那只鹰？
You're ready to pay $5,000 if we turn over the falcon to you?
抱歉！我一定是没有把意思讲清楚
Excuse me, please. I must have expressed myself badly.
钱不在我的口袋里
I did not mean to say that I have the money in my pocket...
银行上班时
...but I am ready to get it for you on a minute's notice...
我随时可以提
...anytime during banking hours.
也许是吧，我下午在办公室搜他时
That's probably true. He only had a couple of hundred...
他身上有几百块
...when I searched him this afternoon at my office.
我会把钱送过来的，早上十点半？
I shall be able to have the money for you at, say, half past 10 in the morning.
我还没拿到鹰呢！
But I haven't got the falcon.
再给我一个礼拜吧
I'll have it in another week at the most, though.
到底在哪里？
Then where is it?
- 佛洛德藏起来了 - 佛洛德藏…
-Where Floyd hid it. -Floyd hid....
你知道在哪里吗？干嘛还要等一个礼拜？
And you know where he hid it? Then why do we have to wait a week?
也许不必一整个礼拜
Oh, perhaps not a whole week.
再问个问题，为什么你会愿意卖给我？
And why, if I may ask another question, are you willing to sell it to me?
佛洛德发生那些事后
Because I'm afraid. After what happened to Floyd...
我很怕碰它
...I'm afraid to touch it,
只想摆脱它
except to turn it over to somebody.
佛洛德怎么了？
What exactly did happen to Floyd?
那个胖男人
The fat man.
Fat man.
- 他在这里？ - 我想是吧
-Is he here? O'SHAUGHNESSY: I don't know.
有什么差别？
I suppose so. What difference does it make?
差别可大了
It might make a world of difference.
对你还是对我？
Or you or me.
要不要处理掉
Precisely. But, shall we add,
外面那家伙？
more certainly the boy outside?
好，但你应该能很好的处理掉他，乔伊
Yes. But you might be able to get around him, Joel...
就像伊斯坦布尔那一回
...as you did the one in Istanbul.
他叫什么名字来着？
What was his name?
你是指那个你无法…
You mean the one you couldn't get to come to--
这是你第二次攻击我
This is the second time that you have laid hands on me.
你挨抽的时候就受着吧
When you're slapped, you'll take it and like it.
那是谁？
Who's that?
不晓得，安静
I don't know. Keep quiet.
你好
SPADE: Hello.
你们可真会挑时间上门啊
You guys pick swell hours to do your visiting in.
- 几点啦？- 我们要事找你聊，史派特
-What is it? -We want to talk to you, Spade.
那就说吧
-Go ahead and talk.
不会让我们站在走廊说吧？
-We don't have to do it in the hall, do we?
- 你们不能进来 - 别瞎掰了，山姆
-You can't come in. -Oh, come off it now, Sam.
你不会是想暴力相向吧？
You aren't trying to strong-arm me, are you, Tom?
讲点道理啊
Why don't you be reasonable?
跟我们玩你会付出代价的，史派德
It would pay you to play along with us.
你逃得过初一
You got away with this and that...
逃不过十五
...but you can't keep it up.
- 行的时候就阻止我 - 我很想这么做
-Stop me when you can. -That's what I intend to do.
有关于你和阿契尔妻子的闲言碎语
There's talk going around about you and Archer's wife.
- 有这回事吗？- 无稽之谈
-Is there anything to it? -Not a thing.
谣言说，阿契尔的太太很想离婚
The talk is she tried to get a divorce
这样才能跟你在一起，他不想离
so she could put in with you. He wouldn't give it.
- 有这回事吗？- 没有
-Anything to that? -No.
谣言说，这就是他被杀的原因
There's talk that that's why he was put on the spot.
别太贪了，邓迪
Don't be a hog, Dundy.
如果你觉得是我杀了麦尔斯的话
Your idea that I killed Thursby because he killed Miles...
那么你起初怀疑我为了麦尔斯 而杀德斯派的假设就不攻而破了
...falls to pieces if you blame me for killing Miles.
我没说过你杀了任何人
You haven't heard me say you killed anybody.
你倒是老提这个
-You're the one bringing that up.
除了老到我这里来 你们就没别的事可干了吗？
-Haven't you anything better to do than to keep popping in here every morning,
老是一大早来问堆蠢问题
asking fool questions?
- 还想要得到假答案 - 不要冲动
-And getting a lot of lying answers. -Take it easy.
如果你说跟阿契尔太太之间是清白的
If you say there's nothing between you and Archer's wife,
那你就是撒谎
you're a liar.
这就是你们会大半夜登门来找我的线索？
Is that the hot tip that brought you up here at this ungodly hour?
这是其中之一
-That's one of them.
其它的呢？
-And the other?
让我们进去
Let us in.
好吧，史派特，我们走就是了
All right, Spade, we'll go.
也许你顶撞我们是对的 再考虑看看吧
Maybe you're right in bucking us. Think it over.
救命啊！
[THUDDING]CAIRO: Help!
- 看来我们得进去了 - 我猜是的
-I guess we're going in. -I guess you are.
怎么回事啊？
DUNDY: What's going on in here?
警官！看看她干了什么好事！
CAIRO: Look. Look, officer. Look what she did.
- 你干的？- 不得不这样
-Did you do that? O'SHAUGHNESSY: I had to.
我和他独处，他想袭击我
I was alone with him. He tried to attack me.
我得让他走开，但我没办法朝他开枪
I couldn't bring myself to shoot him.
你这个肮脏的大骗子！你…不是这样的！
You dirty, filthy liar, you. It isn't true.
我来这里没恶意，他们俩攻击我
I came up here in good faith, and then both of them attacked me.
他出去和你们讲话时 留她和一把手枪在这里
And then when he went out to talk to you, he left her here with a pistol.
她说你们一走，他们就会杀了我
She said as soon as you leave, they are going to kill me...
我才会喊救命 因为我不想你们让我被谋杀
...so I called for help because I didn't want you to leave.
她用手枪敲我
And then she struck me with a pistol.
为什么不逼他讲真话！
O'SHAUGHNESSY: Why don't you make him tell the truth?
注意你的行为，大姐
CAIRO: Look. Look what she.... -Behave yourself, sister.
别演戏了
That's no way to act.
看来我们得带大队人马来了
I don't guess we'll be wrong running the lot of them in.
别急，年青人，一切都好解释
Don't be in a hurry. Everything can be explained.
我敢打赌
I'll bet.
这位是奥夏克尼希小姐
Miss O'Shaughnessy, may I present
邓迪警探，柏郝斯警探
Lieutenant Dundy and Detective Polhaus?
奥夏克尼希小姐昨天起是我的手下
Miss O'Shaughnessy is an operative in my employ since yesterday.
骗人！
That's a lie too.
那是乔伊?开罗先生
That is Mr. Joel Cairo.
开罗跟德斯派很熟 他今天下午来我办公室
Cairo was an acquaintance of Thursby's. He came into my office late this afternoon...
他雇我找东西
...hired me to find something that
德斯派被杀时东西在他手上
Thursby was supposed to have on him.
他说话方式很滑稽，所以我没接手
It looked funny to me the way he put it, so I wouldn't touch it.
他用枪指着我，但这没有关系
Then he pulled a gun on me. Well, that's neither here nor there...
除非我们相互指控
...unless we start preferring charges against each other.
奥夏克尼希小姐和我讨论情况
Miss O'Shaughnessy and I discussed the matter...
决定了解他知道多少
...and decided to find out how much he knew...
麦尔斯和德斯派被杀的内情
...about Miles' and Thursby's killings,
所以我们请他上来
so we asked him to come up here.
可能我们询问的时候的确粗暴了点儿
Now, maybe we did put the questions to him a little roughly.
你是了解状况的，警探
You know how that is, lieutenant.
但我们还没有把他伤到要喊救命
But we didn't hurt him enough to make him cry for help.
- 你想解释什么的吗？- 不知道该说什么
-What have you got to say to that? -I don't know what to say.
说实话吧
Try telling the facts.
- 实话？ - 罗罗嗦嗦
-What? Facts? -Oh, quit stalling.
你只需发誓说他们打了你
All you have to do is swear out a complaint
我就把他们扔进号子
and I'll throw them in the can.
说啊，开罗，告诉他，他会这样的
Go ahead, Cairo. Tell him, he'll do it.
然后我们再发誓指控你 他就把我们都抓住了
Then we'll swear out a complaint against you, and he'll have the lot of us.
去把帽子戴好
Get your hats.
姑娘小伙子们，我们好好解决下
Well, boys and girls, we put it over nicely.
去，拿你的帽子
-Go on, get your hats.
你不知道自己被耍笑了？
-Don't you know when you're being kidded?
不，我们等到了局子再说
No, but that can wait till we get down to the hall.
醒醒吧，邓迪，你被耍笑了
Wake up, Dundy, you're being kidded.
一听到警笛，我就对他们两位说
When I heard the buzzer, I said to Miss O'Shaughnessy and Cairo:
警察又来了，他们还真是讨厌
"There's the police. They're getting to be a nuisance.
听到他们来，你们中的一个就叫
When you hear them going, scream.
然后看把他们耍得团团转能耍多久
We'll see how far we can string them until they tumble."
住嘴，山姆
Stop it, Sam.
他头上是怎么受伤的？
That cut on his head. How did that get there?
- 问他啊，也许是刮胡子时受的伤 - 伤口？不是
-Ask him. Maybe he cut himself shaving. -The cut? No.
我们装着抢手枪 我摔在地毯上，摔的
When we pretended to be struggling for the gun, I fell over the carpet. I fell.
胡说八道！
Horsefeathers.
把他带走，非法持枪
Take him along, anyway, for packing a gun.
别傻了
Don't be a sap.
那枪是个局，枪是我的
That gun was a plant. It was one of mine.
可惜，只是点25，要不你就得证明
Too bad it was only a .25. You could prove that was the gun...
那是凶枪
...Miles and Thursby were shot with.
- 不…山姆…不… - 带他走
-No, Sam. No. -Well, then get him out of here.
- 记下他们的名字和地址 - 乔伊?开罗，了望楼旅馆
-Get their names and addresses. -My name is Joel Cairo, Hotel Belvedere.
奥夏克尼希小姐的地址就是我的办公室
Miss O'Shaughnessy's address is my office.
- 你住哪？ - 让他走！我受够了！
-Where do you live? -Get him out of here.
放松，山姆，这是你想要的，警探？
Take it easy, will you? Is that all you want?
我要走了
-Yeah. -I think I'll be going now.
干嘛那么急？
What's the hurry, Cairo?
不是着急，太晚了
There is no hurry. It's getting quite late, and....
跟他讲不要带走手枪
Tell him to leave the gun.
希望你很清楚自己在干什么，山姆
I hope you know what you're doing, Sam.
你是我这辈子所碰过最野 最难以预料的人
You're absolutely the wildest, most unpredictable person I've ever known.
你总是这么横吗？
Do you always carry on so high-handed?
你已经跟开罗谈过了嘛
Well, you've had your talk with Cairo.
现在你可以跟我谈！
Now you can talk to me.
当然
Oh, yes, of course.
我在听
I'm listening.
我还在听
I'm still listening.
- 看时间，我该走了 - 不行，统统告诉我了再走
-Oh, look at the time. I must be going. -Oh, no. Not till you've told me all about it.
我是囚犯吗？
Am I a prisoner?
也许外面那家伙还没回家
Maybe the boy outside hasn't gone home yet.
他还在那里？
Do you suppose he's still there?
可能
Likely.
开始说吧
You can start now.
你这家伙太固执了
You are the most insistent person.
不但野而且还很难预料，不是吗？
And wild and unpredictable, huh?
这只鸟…这只鹰怎么回事？ 为什么大家这么热衷？
Say, what's this bird, this falcon that everybody's all steamed up about?
如果我什么都不跟你讲
Supposing I wouldn't tell you anything about it at all?
你会怎样？干撒野和难以预料的事？
What would you do? Something wild and unpredictable?
可能喔
I might.
那是一个黑色雕塑，光滑、闪亮…
It's a black figure, as you know, smooth and shiny...
那是一只鸟、鹰，大约这么高
...of a bird, a hawk or falcon, about that high.
我来
Oh, here.
- 它为什么这么重要？- 不晓得，他们不告诉我
-What--? What makes it so important? -I don't know. They wouldn't tell me.
他们付我5百块，如果我能从持有的那个人那里找回来
They offered me ￡500 if I'd help them get it away from the man who had it.
在伊斯坦布尔？
That was in Istanbul?
马尔马拉海
Marmara.
继续说
Go ahead.
就这样了
But that's all.
他们答应，帮他们的话付我5百，我就来了
They promised me ￡500 if I'd help them, and I did.
我们发现乔伊想背弃我们
Then we found out that Joel Cairo intended to desert us...
独吞那只鹰
...taking the falcon with him and leaving Floyd and me nothing.
所以我们就那样对付他
So we did exactly that to him.
但情况一点没好转
Then I wasn't any better off than before.
因为佛洛德也不打算信守诺言
Floyd hadn't any intention of keeping his promise...
平分，我们到这里后我才了解的
...about sharing. I learned that by the time we got here.
那只鸟什么材质？
What's the bird made of?
瓷或者黑石…不晓得 我只看过一次，而且只几分钟
Porcelain or black stone. I don't know. I only saw it for a few minutes.
我们第一次拿到的时候佛洛德给我看过
Floyd showed it to me when we first got hold of it.
你撒谎
You are a liar.
没错
I am.
我一直在撒谎
I've always been a liar.
别自吹自擂
Don't brag about it.
这奇谈里有没有什么值得相信的？
Was there any truth at all in that yarn?
一些些
Some.
不多就是了
Not very much.
我们有的是时间
Well, we got all night.
咖啡马上准备好，喝了咖啡重新再来
Coffee'll be ready soon. We'll have a cup and try again.
我很累了
Oh, I'm so tired.
厌倦了撒谎
So tired of lying and making up lies.
我已经分不清哪些是谎言 哪些是真话了，我希望…
Not knowing what is a lie and what's the truth. I wish....
我要跟开罗先生谈，乔伊?开罗
I want to talk to Mr. Cairo, Joel Cairo.
谢谢
Oh. Thanks.
他在哪里？
Where is he?
- 什么？- 他在哪里？
-What? -Where is he?
- 谁啊？- 开罗
-Who?
-Cairo.
你想干嘛？逗我玩吗？
What do you think you're doing, Jack, kidding me?
我要逗你的时候会告诉你
I'll tell you when I am.
纽约，不是吗？
New York, aren't you?
走开！
Shove off.
你必须先开口跟我讲，年青人
You're gonna have to talk to me before you're through.
你们有人会的，转告那个胖男人
Some of you will, and you can tell the fat man I said so.
继续问吧，你会得到的，很多
Keep asking for it and you're gonna get it. Plenty.
我叫你走开！
I told you to shove off.
走开！
Shove off.
很多人这样讲话没了牙齿
People lose teeth talking like that.
你想在这里混，就礼貌点
You wanna hang around, you'll be polite.
卢克
Luke.
- 你好，山姆 - 你好，卢克
-Hello, Sam. -Hello, Luke.
麦尔斯的事太遗憾了
Say, that was too bad about Miles.
是啊，是个惊天意外
Yeah. It was a tough break.
我有东西给你看
I want to show you something.
你干嘛让这些廉价的枪手在大厅里晃荡
What do you let these cheap gunmen hang around for...
他们的铳子都凸出来了
...with their heaters bulging in their clothes?
你想干嘛？
What do you want here?
如果没什么事的话，闪人吧
Well, if you don't want anything, beat it
不要再来
and don't come back.
我不会忘记你们的
I won't forget you guys.
- 什么状况？- 不晓得，我刚刚发现他
-What is it? -I don't know. I just spotted him.
- 麦尔斯那里怎样？- 回见，卢克
-Say, what about Miles? -I'll see you, Luke.
- 603 - 是，先生
-Six-oh-three. -Yes, sir.
早安
Good morning.
- 早安 - 给你，先生
-Good morning.-There you are.
找个地方聊聊吧
Let's go someplace where we can talk.
不，我可没什么兴趣继续
Our conversations have not been such that
我们的私下谈话
I'm anxious to continue them.
原谅我的粗鲁，但事实如此
Forgive my speaking so bluntly, but it is the truth.
你是指昨晚的事？我能怎么样？
You mean last night?
我必须站在她那边，我不知道鸟在哪里
I had to throw in with her.
你也不知道，只有她知道
I don't know where the bird is. She does.
如果我不和她周旋我们怎么搞得到？
How we gonna get it if I don't play along?
你总是能自圆其说
You always have a very smooth explanation ready, huh?
难道要我口吃不成？
What do you want me to do? Learn to stutter?
邓迪带你去警局了？他们盘问了你多久？
Dundy take you to the station? How long they work on you?
直到刚才
Till a little while ago.
- 他们抖落出你什么没有？- 抖落？没有
-What'd they shake out of you? -Shake out? Not one thing.
我坚持你晚上的说辞
I adhered to the course you indicated earlier in your rooms...
但我真希望你编得更像一点
...but I certainly wish you would have invented a more reasonable story.
重复那些我自己都觉得蠢
I felt distinctly like an idiot repeating it.
别在意那些胡扯
Don't worry about the story's goofiness.
编得太合理可能害我们都坐牢了
A sensible one would have had us all in the cooler.
- 你确定什么都没讲吗？- 没有
-You sure you didn't tell them anything? -I did not.
你现在肯定想睡了
Now, you'll want sleep
如果你整晚都被警察盘问
if you've been standing up under a police grilling all night.
- 回见
See you later.
- 不，还不行
No, not yet.
他来后我会请他给你打电话
Yes, I'll have him call you the minute he comes in.
这是她今天早上的第三通电话
That's the third time she's called this morning.
- 奥夏克尼希小姐在里面 - 还有呢？
-Miss O'Shaughnessy's in there. -Anything else?
区检察官打过电话来，布莱恩想见你
The district attorney's office called. Bryan would like to see you.
还有个叫顾德曼的打过电话给你
And a Mr. Gutman called. When I told him you weren't in...
我说你不在，他说：请你转告他
...he said, "Tell him the young man...
那个年青人给我留了口信 我打过电话，还会再打来
...gave me his message, and that I phoned and will phone again?"
顾德曼？
Gutman, huh?
谢啦，亲爱的
Thanks, darling.
亲爱的，有人去过我公寓
Darling. Somebody's been in my apartment.
到处翻得乱七八糟
It's all upside down, every which way.
我一换好地方就来这里了
I changed as fast as I could and came right over here.
你肯定是被那家伙跟踪了
-You must have let that boy follow you. -No, angel.
不，亲爱的，我到你那儿 之前很久就甩掉他了
I shook him off long before I ever went to your place.
可能是开罗，他昨晚不在酒店
It might have been Cairo. He wasn't at the hotel last night.
开罗说，他一整夜都被警察盘问
He told me he'd been standing up under a police grilling. I wonder.
- 今天早上有没有看到乔伊？- 看到了
-You saw Joel this morning? -Yeah.
干嘛？
Why?
因为，我亲爱的，我得跟进各种线索
Because I've gotta keep in some sort of touch...
才能从这一团乱麻中理出头绪来
...with all the loose ends of this dizzy affair if I'm ever gonna make heads or tails of it.
现在我们得给你找个新家
Now we've got to find a new home for you.
我不想回去
I won't go back there.
我想到了，等等
I got an idea. Wait a minute.
凭你的女性直觉，你觉得她怎样？
What does your woman's intuition tell you about her?
她还好，也许出这些麻烦是她自找的
She's all right. Maybe it's her own fault
但她还好，如果你是这意思
for being in trouble, but she's all right.
我就是这意思
Are you strong enough for her
你有没有能力藏她几天？
to put her up for a few days?
- 你是说在家 - 是的
-You mean at home? -Yeah.
- 她有危险，山姆？- 是的
-Is she in any danger, Sam? -I think she is.
会吓死我妈的
Gee, that'd scare Mom into a green hemorrhage.
我得说她是目击证人之类的
I'd have to say she's a surprise witness
你得一直瞒着
you're keeping undercover.
你真体贴
You're a darling.
布瑞怡
Oh, Brigid.
爱菲说她可以收容你住几天
Effie offered to put you up for a few days.
谢谢好意
That's very kind.
你们最好动身，从后面出去
You'd better start now. Go out the back.
小巷里通常有辆出租停着的
There's usually a cab parked there.
在半路桥上下车，确认没人跟踪
Ride partway with her and make sure you're not followed.
最好多换几辆计程车，以确保安全
Change cabs a couple of times, just to be safe.
我会打电话给妈妈
I'll give Mom a ring.
等你回去大把时间可以
There's time enough for that when you get back.
待会儿再联络
I'll call you later.
喂？
Hello?
我是山姆?史派特
This is Samuel Spade.
我的秘书说布莱恩先生要见我
Say, my secretary tells me Mr. Bryan wants to see me.
是的，请问他什么时间最合适
Yeah. Ask him what time's most convenient for him.
史派特
Spade. S-P-A-D-E.
嗨，甜心
Hello, honey.
嗯
Yeah.
两点半，好，谢谢
Two-thirty. All right. Thanks.
山姆，请原谅我
Oh, Sam, forgive me. Please forgive me.
是我昨晚叫警察到你那里的
I sent those policemen to your place last night.
我被醋意冲昏头了 我打电话叫他们过去
I was mad, crazy with jealousy.
说会发现麦尔斯谋杀的线索
I phoned that if they went there they'd learn something about Miles' murder.
- 你怎么会这么想？- 我疯了，山姆，我想伤害你
-What made you think of that? -I was mad. I wanted to hurt you.
你打电话时告诉警察你的身份吗？
Did you tell them who you were?
- 没有，山姆，最亲爱的，我…- 你从哪里打电话的？
-No. Sam, dearest, I--Where'd you phone from?
你街对过的药店
-The drugstore across from your place.
你最好赶紧回家想一些话来应付警察
-You better hurry home...and think of something to tell the police.
他们会找你的，顺便问下
And by the way...
麦尔斯遇害那晚，你在什么地方？
...where were you the night Miles was murdered?
家里
Home.
- 我真的在家！- 没有
-I was. -No.
但我不会追究你的故事
But if that's your story, it's all right with me.
你走吧
Now you run along.
喂？
Hello?
我是史派特
Yeah, this is Spade.
是的，顾德曼先生，我拿到了 一直在等你的消息
Oh, yes, Mr. Gutman, I got it. I've been waiting to hear from you.
越快越好，15分钟如何？好的
Well, now. The sooner, the better. Say, 15 minutes? Right.
好，12C
Twelve-C.
你左边的12C
Twelve-C to your left, sir.
- 啊，史派特先生- 你好，顾德曼先生？
-Mr. Spade. -How do you do, Mr. Gutman?
你开局不错
You begin well, sir.
我不相信说“何时”的人
I distrust a man who says when.
他得当心酒后失言
He's got to be careful not to drink too much...
因为他这样做的时候，是不被信任的
...because he's not to be trusted when he does.
好吧，先生
Well, sir...
我们就为开诚布公与清楚的沟通干一杯
...here's to plain speaking and clear understanding.
- 你是个守口如瓶的人吗？- 不，我喜欢说话
-You're a close-mouthed man? -No, I like to talk.
我越来越欣赏你 我不信任守口如瓶的人
Better and better. I distrust a close-mouthed man.
这种人开口的时机通常都会不对，也通常会说错话
He generally picks the wrong time to talk and says the wrong things.
明智的说话并不容易 除非时常练习
Talking's something you can't do judiciously unless you keep in practice.
现在，先生，我们就开说吧
Now, sir. We'll talk, if you like.
直说吧，我喜欢跟爱说话的人说话
I'll tell you right out. I am a man who likes talking to a man who likes to talk.
很好
Swell.
谈谈黑鸟怎么样？
Will we talk about the black bird?
你正合我的胃口
[CHUCKLES] You're a man for me, sir.
不会拐弯抹角，说话直截了当
No beating about the bush. Right to the point.
我们就来谈黑鸟
Let's talk about the black bird, by all means.
请先回答一个问题
But first, answer me a question.
你代表奥夏克尼希小姐吗？
Are you here as Miss O'Shaughnessy's representative?
并不一定，视情况而定
Well, there's nothing certain either way. It depends.
看什么情况？
Depends on?
也许要看乔伊?开罗的
Maybe it depends on Joel Cairo.
也许
Maybe.
问题是你代表谁？非此即彼
The question is then which you represent. It'll be one or the other.
我没有这么说
I didn't say so.
- 还有谁呢？- 还有我自己
-Who else is there? -There's me.
了不起，先生，了不起
Ah. Ha-ha. That's wonderful, sir, wonderful.
我喜欢一个人坦白地表示他为自己着想
I do like a man who tells you right out he's looking out for himself.
我们不都是如此吗？
Don't we all?
我不信任自称不自私的人
I don't trust a man who says he's not.
让我们来谈黑鸟
Uh-huh. Now, let's talk about the black bird.
来吧
Let's.
史派特先生，你了不了解
Mr. Spade, have you any conception...
那只黑鸟可以弄来多少钱吗？
...of how much money can be got for that black bird?
不知道
No.
我说个半价，你都会觉得我在骗人
Well, sir, if I told you, if I told you half, you'd call me a liar.
不会，就算我这么想也不会
No, not even if I thought so.
你告诉我那是什么 我自己会算出来价码
But you tell me what it is, and I'll figure out the profit.
你不知道黑鸟是什么？
You mean, you don't know what the bird is?
我知道它什么样
Oh, I know what it's supposed to look like...
我也知道你们不惜杀人
...and I know the value in human life you people put on it.
她没有告诉你那是什么？
She didn't tell you what it is?
- 开罗也没有告诉你？- 他出价1万元
-Cairo didn't, either? -He offered me 10,000 for it.
1万元
Ten thousand.
是美元，不是英镑
Dollars, mind you, not even pounds.
他们知道黑鸟是什么吗？你的印象是怎样的？
Do they know what that bird is, sir? What is your impression?
没什么
Not much to go by.
开罗没有说他知道，也没说不知道
Cairo didn't say he did, didn't say he didn't.
而她说她不知道，但我认为她在说谎
She said she didn't, but I took it for granted she was lying.
我的判断不是没理由的
Not an injudicious thing to do.
如果他们都不知道 那我是全世界唯一知道的
If they don't know, I'm the only one in the whole wide sweet world who does.
告诉了我就只有我们俩知道
Swell. When you've told me, that'll make two of us.
算术上是正确的 先生，但我不确定是否要告诉你
Mathematically correct, sir, but I don't know for certain that I'm going to tell you.
别傻了，你知道它是什么 我知道它在哪里，所以我才在这里
Don't be foolish. I know where it is. That's why I'm here.
它在哪里？
Well, sir, where is it?
我必须告诉你我所知道的，但你却不肯告诉我
You see, I must tell you what I know, but you won't tell me what you know.
太不公平了
It's hardly equitable, sir.
不行，不行，我们这样子是无法交易的
No, no. I don't think we can do business along those lines.
再考虑考虑，而且要快！
Well, think again, and think fast.
我告诉过你的打手 你想搞定这事就得先告诉我
I told that gunsel you'd talk to me before you're through.
我现在告诉你，你要不今天告诉我，要不你自己搞定！
You'll talk to me today, or you are through.
不要浪费我的时间！没有你我也可以干
What are you wasting my time for? I can get along without you.
还有
And
你在下决心的时候别让那打手靠近我
keep that gunsel out of my way while you're making up your mind.
我会杀了他！我会杀了他！
I'll kill him if you don't. I'll kill him.
你的性格真是暴力
Well, sir, I must say you have a most violent temper.
好好考虑，给你到五点钟
SPADE:Think it over. You've got till 5:00.
到时候你不是加入就是退出，永远！
Then you're either in or out, for keeps.
- 谁杀了德斯派？- 我不知道
-Who killed Thursby? SPADE: I don't know.
可能你没有，但你可以猜得很准
Perhaps, but you could make an excellent guess.
我的猜想可能很准，可能毫无价值
My guess might be excellent or crummy,
但史派德养出的小孩可不会笨到
but Mrs. Spade didn't raise any children...
在检察官，助理检察官和速记员面前乱猜
...dippy enough to make guesses in front of a district attorney and a stenographer.
你为什么不猜呢？如果你没有什么想隐瞒的
Why, if you've nothing to conceal?
每个人都有所隐瞒
Everybody has something to conceal.
我是宣过誓的执法官，一天24小时都是
I'm a sworn officer of the law, 24 hours a day...
你没有权利向我隐瞒犯罪证据
...and neither formality nor informality justifies you withholding...
当然除了基于宪法权利之外
...evidence of crime from me except, of course, on constitutional grounds.
你与警方都指控我
Both you and the police have accused me...
涉及这桩谋杀案
...of being mixed up in the murders.
我和你们俩以前都有过节，在我看来
I've had trouble with both of you before, and as far as I can see...
要想洗清你们泼给我的脏水
...my best chance of clearing myself of the trouble...
我只能自己将凶手绳之以法
...is bringing in the murderers all tied up.
如果想抓住凶手
The only chance I've got of tying them up
绳之以法
and bringing them in...
我就必须尽量躲开你与警察
...is by staying away from you and the police.
你们只会坏事
You'd gum up the works.
你都记下了，还是我说得太快了吗？
You getting this all right? Am I going too fast?
- 我都记下来了- 不简单
No, sir. I'm getting it all right.
如果你想告诉委员会我妨碍司法公正
Good work. If you want to go to the board and tell them I'm obstructing justice...
要求他们撤销我的执照，就快去
...and ask them to revoke my license, hop to it.
你们以前试过，结果只换来嘲笑
You tried it before, and it didn't get you anything.
- 你给我听着…- 我不想再进行非正式谈话
-Now, look here. -I don't want any more informal talks.
我对你或警察都无话好说 我已经厌倦了
I've nothing to say to you, and I'm tired of being called things...
被每个想入非非的公务员呼来唤去，如果想见我
...by every crackpot on the city payroll. So, if you want to see me...
拘留我或者传唤我 我会找律师一起来
...pinch me or subpoena me or something, and I'll come down with my lawyer.
也许我会在审讯时见到你
I'll see you at the inquest, maybe.
来吧，他要见你
Come on. He wants to see you.
我还以为5：25之前你不会来 希望你没有久等
I didn't expect you till 5:25. I hope I haven't kept you waiting.
如果继续嘲弄我
Keep on riding me,
别人就得从你的肝脏找枪子
they're gonna be picking iron out of your liver.
越低级的混混，越爱装腔作势
[SPADE CHUCKLES] The cheaper the crook, the gaudier the patter, huh?
我们走
Now, let's go.
走啊，这会让你在老板面前受宠的
Come on. This'll put you in solid with your boss.
请进，先生，谢谢你过来
Come in, sir. Thank you for coming. Come in.
给，你不应该让他带着这些走来走去
You shouldn't let him go around with these on him.
他也许会弄伤自己
He might get himself hurt.
啊，这是什么？
Well, well, what's this?
被一个跛脚的报童抢走了 后来又被我抢回来
A crippled newsie took them away from him. I made him give them back.
哎呀，你是个值得交往的人物 性格迷人，把帽子给我
By gad, sir, you're a chap worth knowing. An amazing character. Give me your hat.
坐下
Sit down.
- 我必须向你道歉，先生- 别介意
-I owe you an apology, sir. SPADE: Now, never mind that.
让我们谈谈黑鸟
Let's talk about the black bird.
好吧，我们来谈
All right, sir, let's.
我们来谈
Let's.
这将是你所听过最令人吃惊的一件事
This is going to be the most astounding thing you've ever heard of, sir.
即使我知道你是这样见多识广的人
I say this knowing that a man of your caliber and profession...
你一定知道许多令人惊讶的事
...must have known some astounding things in his time.
你有没有听说过
What do you know about the Order of the Hospital of Saint John of Jerusalem...
耶路撒冷圣约翰骑士团？
...later known as the Knights of Rhodes?
- 他们是十字军什么的，是不是？- 很好，坐下
-Crusaders or something, weren't they? -Very good. Sit down.
1539年，这些十字军骑士
In 1539, these crusading knights...
说服查理五世赐给他们马耳他岛
...persuaded Emperor Charles V to give them the island of Malta.
他只提出一个条件
He made but one condition,
他们每年进贡一只老鹰
that they pay him each year the tribute of a falcon...
借此承认马耳他岛仍然属西班牙治下
...in acknowledgement that Malta was still under Spain.
你明白我说的吗？
-Do you follow me? -Uh-huh.
你能想像当时
Have you any conception of the extreme,
骑士团有多富裕吗？
the immeasurable wealth of the Order?
我想他们混得相当不错
-I imagine they were pretty well fixed. -"Pretty well" is putting it mildly.
他们富可敌国，先生
They were rolling in wealth, sir.
他们数年来掠夺东方 没有人知道多有少珠宝
For years they'd taken from the East nobody knows what spoils of gems...
贵重金属，丝绸与象牙
...precious metals, silks, ivory, sir.
圣战对他们来说就是烧杀抢掠
We all know the holy wars to them were largely a matter of loot.
武士们都很感激查理五世
The knights were profoundly grateful to the Emperor Charles...
对他们的慷慨
...for his generosity toward them.
他们偶尔想到
They hit upon the thought of sending him for his first year's tribute...
第一年的进贡，不是一只微不足道的活鸟
...not an insignificant live bird...
而是一只黄金老鹰
...but a glorious golden falcon
从头到脚镶满了
crusted from head to foot...
最好的珠宝
...with the finest jewels in their coffers.
先生
-Well, sir,
- 你觉得怎样？- 我不知道
what do you think of that? -I don't know.
这都是事实，历史事实
These are facts, historical facts.
不是教科书的历史，但是历史没错
Not schoolbook history, not Mr. Wells' history, but history, nevertheless.
他们把这只一英尺高的珠宝 老鹰进贡给西班牙国王查理
They sent this jeweled bird to Charles, who was then in Spain.
骑士团一名成员驾船运送这只金鹰
They sent it in a galley commanded by a member of the Order.
但从未抵达西班牙
It never reached Spain.
一个著名的海盗骑劫了
A famous admiral of buccaneers
骑士的船和金鹰
took the knights' galley and the bird.
1713年金鹰出现在意大利西西里
In 1713, it turned up in Sicily.
1840年又出现在巴黎
In 1840, it appeared in Paris.
被人涂上一层黑瓷釉
It had, by that time, acquired a coat of black enamel...
看起来像个很古怪的黑色雕像
...so that it looked nothing more than a fairly interesting black statuette.
在这种伪装下，它在巴黎到处流落
In that disguise, sir, it was, as you may say, kicked around Paris...
超过了60年，拥有者都非常愚蠢
...for over three score years by private owners too stupid...
看不出表面下的宝藏
...to see what it was under the skin.
直到
Then, heh-heh,
1923年
in 1923,
一位希腊商人，名叫卡罗斯康 斯坦丁在一家小店里发现它
a Greek dealer named Charilaos Konstantinides ...found it in an obscure shop.
不论是多么厚的瓷釉掩盖 都逃不过他的精明眼光
No thickness of enamel could conceal value from his eyes.
- 你开始有点相信我了吗？ - 我没有说我不相信
-You begin to believe me a little? -I haven't said I didn't.
为了在研究它的历史时，又能保证安全
Well, sir, to hold it safe while pursuing his researches into its history...
他给它重新上了一层漆
...Charilaos re-enameled the bird.
尽管有这层保护措施，我还是收到了风
Despite this precaution, however, I got wind of his find.
如果早几天知道就好了
If I'd only known a few days sooner.
我听说此事时在伦敦
I was in London
我立刻收拾行李，踏上港口联运列车
when I heard. I packed a bag, got on the boat train immediately.
在火车上，我打开泰晤士报
On the train I opened the paper,
看到卡罗斯的家遭劫
and read that Charilaos' establishment...
他被谋杀了
...had been burglarized and him murdered.
果不其然，等我到达那里后发现鸟儿已经不见了
Sure enough, on arriving there, I discovered the bird was gone.
那是17年前的事了
That was 17 years ago.
我花了17年才找到那只鸟的踪迹，但我找到了
Well, sir, it took me 17 years to locate that bird, but I did.
我要得到它
I wanted it.
我不会轻言放弃
I'm a man not easily discouraged when I want something.
一直追查到一位俄国将军身上
I traced it to the home of a Russian general, one Kemidov...
他叫卡马多夫，住在伊斯坦布尔，他一无所知
...in an Istanbul suburb. He didn't know a thing about it.
对他而言，那只是个油漆雕像
It was nothing but a black-enameled figure to him...
但他天生爱唱反调，所以不愿意卖给我
...but his contrariness kept him from selling it...
我派出一些“干员”去取得它
...when I made him an offer. So I sent him some agents to get it.
先生
Well, sir,
他们弄到了，但还没到我手上
they got it and I haven't got it.
我一定会得到它
But I'm going to get it.
你的酒杯
Your glass.
那么鸟儿并不属于你们而是属于卡马多夫将军
Then the bird doesn't really belong to any of you, but to a General Kemidov?
你为何不干脆说它属于西班牙国王
Well, sir, you might as well say it belonged to the King of Spain.
你又能说谁真正拥有它呢？
I don't see how you can honestly grant anyone else a clear title to it...
只能是谁有就是谁的
...except by right of possession.
现在
And now, sir...
在我们谈价码前，你需要多少时间…
...before we start to talk prices,
才能拿到或者说愿意给出那只鸟？
how soon can you, or how soon are you willing...
- 几天吧 - 这我可以接受
-...to produce the falcon? -Couple of days. That is satisfactory.
祝我们的公平交易顺利，大家有钱赚
Well, sir, here's to a fair bargain. Profits large enough for both of us.
你所谓公平交易是什么？
What's your idea of a fair bargain?
等你给我金鹰后 我会给你美金2万5千元
I will give you $25,000 when you deliver the falcon to me...
稍后再给你2万5千元
...and another 25,000 later on.
或者我会给你那只金鹰价值的四分之一
Or I will give you one quarter of what I realize on the falcon.
那将是一笔庞大的数目
That would amount to a greater sum.
- 多么庞大？ - 谁知道呢？10万美元？
-How much greater? -Who knows? Shall we say 100,000?
如果我说出个可能的最低价 你会相信我吗？
Would you believe me if I name a sum that seems probable?
有何不可？
Why not?
25万美元怎么样？
What would you say to a quarter of a million?
你认为那玩意儿值1百万？
Then you think the dingus is worth a million, huh?
以你的话说，有何不可？
In your own words, why not?
- 那是一大笔钱 - 一大笔钱
-That's a lot of dough. -A lot of dough.
最低价？那么最高价呢？
-Minimum, huh? What's the maximum?
我拒绝猜测最高价
-The maximum, I refuse to guess.
你会认为我疯了
You'd think me crazy.
我不知道
I don't know.
谁也不知道它会去到多高价，先生
There's no telling how high it could go, sir.
这是我唯一确知的事实
That is the one and only truth about it.
威曼！
Wilmer.
喂，爱菲，是我
Hello, Effie. It's me.
让我跟奥夏克尼希小姐说话
Let me talk to Miss O'Shaughnessy.
不在？
Isn’t there?
什么？她没出现？
What? She didn't show up?
回到办公室等我回来或打电话
Oh. You get on back to the office and wait there till I come or you hear from me.
这次我们要做对事情来倒倒运了
Yeah, let's do something right for a change.
船运消息：今天到埠 下午5：35香港出发的鸽子号
舱尾开始起火，在底舱
It started in the hold aft, in the rear basement.
她保了什么险？
What insurance was she carrying?
- 有人烧伤吗？ - 没有
-Anybody burnt? -No.
只有碇泊值班在船上
Only the harbor watch was aboard.
- 我认识的一个人来… - 什么？
-Someone I know came-- -Huh?
我认识的一个人下午上了船
Someone I know came aboard this afternoon...
我一直没见她，我很担心
...and I haven't seen her since. I'm worried.
不需要担心，先生，大家都脱险了
No reason to be, mister. Everybody got off all right.
不知道你有没有看到她？ 个子小小的，大约1米6高…
I wonder if you saw her. She's kind of small, about 5-foot--
不好说，但如果她上了船，她也下了船
I couldn't tell you, mister. But if she come aboard, she got off all right.
火灾开始时，船上只有碇泊值班
Only the harbor watch was aboard when the fire started.
现在你知道得跟我一样多，亲爱的
Now you know as much about it as I do, precious.
也许他们上船了，也许没有
Maybe they went down to the ship. Maybe they didn't.
关于鸟的故事很惊人
The part about the bird is thrilling.
或者很荒唐
Or ridiculous.
你知道…
You know.
老鹰…
Falcon.
锁上门！
Lock that door.
他…
Is...?
- 他是不是… - 没错
Is he...? Yeah.
身上有这么多洞，他也走不远
He couldn't have come far with those holes in him.
他为什么不能活久一点，告诉我们一些事情？
Why couldn't he have stayed alive long enough to tell us something?
看这里，别看那里了
Here, here, here, none of that now. Come on.
- 你可不要给我昏倒 - 好的，山姆
-You can't pass out on me now. -All right, Sam.
你想是不是…
Do you really think it's...?
- 我们拿到了，天使我们拿到了！- 你弄疼我了
-We've got it, angel, we've got it. -You're hurting me.
接电话
Answer the phone.
喂？
Hello.
是的
[WOMAN SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY OVER PHONE]
谁？
Yes. Who?
噢，是的！
Oh, yes.
哪里？
Where?
好的，好
Yes, yes.
喂？喂？喂？
Hello? Hello. Hello.
奥夏克尼希小姐需要你，她正身处危险
That was Miss O'Shaughnessy. She's in danger.
- 她在什么地方？- 柏林根安萧路26号
-Where is she? -Burlingame, 26 Ancho.
山姆，她的嗓音很糟糕
Sam, her voice, it was awful.
她还没说完话就出事了 去救她，山姆！
Something happened to her before she could finish. Go help her.
你得去救她，他要救她，结果被杀了
You've got to go to her. He was helping her, and they killed him.
你一定要去，山姆
You've got to go, Sam.
好，我去
All right, I'll go.
等我走了，打电话报警
After I've gone, you phone the police.
告诉他们事情经过 但不要扯出任何名字，你不知道
Tell them how it happened, but don't drag names in.
我接到电话就告诉你要出去了 但没说去哪里
I got the phone call and told you I had to go, but didn't say where.
这个先别管了，告诉他们事情经过 但不要提到这个包裹
Forget this. Tell them how it happened, without the bundle.
现在理顺下，发生的事情照实说
Get that straight. Everything happened exactly as it did...
但别提包裹，是我接到电话，不是你
...but without the bundle, and I got the phone call, not you.
- 好，山姆 - 好
-Yes, Sam. -Okay.
锁好门，警察来后再开门
Shut this door and lock it behind me. Don't open it till the police come.
他是谁？
Do you know who he is?
耶哥船长，鸽子号的主人
Yeah. Yeah, he's Captain Jacoby, master of the La Paloma.
你是个好女孩
You're a good man, sister.
- 借支笔好吗？- 好的
-Can I borrow your pencil? -Sure.
- 喂，法兰克 - 嗨，史派特先生
-Say, Frank. -Oh, hello, Mr. Spade.
- 气还足够用吗？- 当然
-You got plenty of gas? -Sure thing.
知不知道柏林根安萧路？
Do you know where Ancho Street is in Burlingame?
不知道，但可以找得到
-Nope, but we can find her.
去26号，越快越好
-Twenty-six is the number...
好的
-...and the sooner the better. -All right.
不要熄火
Keep your motor running.
- 假情报，史派特先生？- 是的
-Bum steer, Mr. Spade? -Yeah.
去找个电话亭
Let's get to a phone booth.
喂，柏琳太太？爱菲在吗？
Hello, Mrs. Perine? Is Effie there?
请叫她来听电话
Yes, please.
嗨，亲爱的，有什么好消息？
Hello, precious. What's the good news?
没有，那是假情报，你确定那是她的声音？
No, no. It was a bum steer. Are you sure that was her voice?
是骗人的
Well, it was hooey.
一切都没有问题？没有提到包裹吧？
Everything go all right? Nothing said about the bundle, huh?
好极了
That's swell.
他们有没有带你到局子里
They take you down to the hall?
好，亲爱的
All right.
好好睡一觉，你听上去疲惫极了
You better hit the hay and get a good night's rest. You sound all in.
不，等明天再说，我要回家了
No, no. Save it till tomorrow. I'm going on home.
- 谢谢，晚安，法兰克 - 晚安，史派特先生
-Thanks. Good night, Frank. -Good night, Mr. Spade.
我一直躲在街上门边
O'SHAUGHNESSY: I've been hiding in a doorway up the street.
还以为你不回来了
I thought you'd never come.
你走得动吗？还是要我背你？
Can you make it, or shall I carry you?
等我躺下来就没事了
I'll be all right as soon as I can get some place where I can lie down.
先生，我们都到了
Well, sir, we're all here.
让我们坐下舒舒服服地谈谈
Now, let's come in and sit down and be comfortable and talk.
当然
SPADE:Sure.
- 走开，休想搜我身 - 站好，闭嘴
-Get away. You're not gonna frisk me. -Stand still. Shut up.
把你的爪子拿开，要不你就开枪
Take your paws off me, or I'll make you use that gun.
问问你老板想不想我说话前就中枪？
Ask your boss if he wants me shot up before we talk.
算了，威曼
Never mind, Wilmer.
你简直顽固到家
You certainly are a most headstrong individual.
让我们坐下来
Well, let's be seated.
你准备付头期拿走老鹰吗？
Are you ready to make the first payment and take the falcon off my hands?
先生，关于这交易…
Well, sir, as to that....
关于…
As to that....
1万元？我们谈的时候比这更多
Ten thousand? We were talking about a lot more money than this.
此一时彼一时，但这可是真金白银啊
Yes, sir, we were. But this is genuine coin of the realm.
一块钱能买十块钱的情报
With a dollar of this, you can buy $10 of talk.
现在我们可有更多人要照料了
And there are more of us to be taken care of now.
也许，但老鹰在我手上
That may be, but I've got the falcon.
史派特先生，我不必提醒你
I shouldn't think it necessary to remind you, Mr. Spade...
你有老鹰，但我们有你
...that you may have the falcon, but we certainly have you.
我正想忘记这烦心事呢 我们等下再谈钱
I'm trying not to let that worry me. We'll get back to the money later on.
先要讨论一件事
There's something else to be discussed first.
我们必须要有替罪羊
We've got to have a fall guy.
警方需要有人
The police have gotta have a victim,
为三件谋杀案顶罪
somebody they can pin those murders on.
三件？只有两件啊 你的同事是被德斯派杀的
Three? But there's only two, because Thursby certainly killed your partner.
好吧，就两件，那有什么区别？
Only two, what difference does it make?
关键是，我们必须给警方…
-We've got to give the police-- -Come, come, Mr. Spade.
得了，史派德先生 别指望我们相信这个时候
You can't expect us to believe at this late date...
你会害怕警察
...that you're the least bit afraid of the police.
- 或你没有办法处理…- 我已经陷得太深了，顾德曼
-Or that you're not able to handle-- -I'm in this up to my neck.
到时候一定要找一个替罪羊 如果没有，我就会成为替罪羊
I've got to find somebody, a victim, when the time comes. If I don't, I'll be it.
让我们把这位杀手给警方
Let's give them the gunsel.
他杀了德斯派与耶哥，对不对？
He actually did shoot Thursby and Jacoby, didn't he?
他简直像是订做的，看看他
Anyway, he's made to order for the part. Look at him.
交出他吧
Let's give him to them.
天，你真有性格
By gad, sir, you are a character.That you are.
没有人能猜得出你下一步会怎么做
There's never any tellingwhat you'll say or do next...
但一定会叫人吃惊
...except that it's boundto be astonishing.
这是最好的办法，把他交给他们…
-It's our best bet. With him in their hands--
我根本不会想这种事，哪怕一瞬间
-My dear man, can't you see...
简直荒谬透顶
...that if I, even for a moment thoughtof doing such a thing.... That's ridiculous.
威曼就像是我的儿子
I feel towards Wilmer here just exactlyas if he were my own son.
真的
Really, I do.
就算我考虑到了你的建议
But if I even for a momentthought of doing what you propose...
要怎么样才能使威曼不告诉警方
...what in the world would keep Wilmer from telling the police...
所有关于老鹰的事情？
...every last detailabout the falcon and all--
随便他讲破天
Let him talk his head off.
我保证没有人会理会他
I'll guarantee you nobody'll do anything about it.
你觉得如何，威曼？真好笑
Well, well, what do you think of this,Wilmer? Mighty funny.
真好笑
Mighty funny.
感觉好些吗，亲爱的？
How do you feel now?Any better, precious?
好多了
[WHISPERING]Much better.
但我害怕
But I'm frightened.
不要害怕，不会发生什么坏事
Well, don't be.Nothing very bad's going to happen here.
想喝点什么吗，亲爱的？
You want a drink, angel?
小心点，山姆
Be careful, Sam.
怎么样？
Well?
看你这么认真
If you're really serious,
我们礼貌上应该听你说说
the least we can doin common politeness is hear you out.
但你要怎么做
Now, how would you be able to fix it
才不会让威曼牵累我们？
so that Wilmer couldn't do us any harm?
我可以告诉区检察官布莱恩 如果他想要
I can show our district attorney, that if he goes around...
大肆拉人，他就会有件棘手案子
...trying to collect everybody,he's gonna have a tangled case...
但如果就他钉死这个威曼
...but if he sticks to Wilmer here...
他就可以不费吹灰之力定罪
...he can get a conviction standing on his head.
站起来
Get up on your feet.
我受够你了
I've taken all the riding from you I'm gonna take.
起来，拼个你死我活
Get up and shoot it out.
西部枪神
Young Wild West.
也许你最好告诉他
Tell him that shooting me before you get your hands on the falcon...
没拿到老鹰前就杀了我 是很糟糕的做法
...is gonna be bad for business.
好了，好了，威曼，不能再闹了
Now, now, Wilmer. We can't have any of that.
你不该让自己扯上这么重要的事情
You shouldn't let yourself attach importance to these things.
叫他别扯我进来
-Then tell him to lay off me.
好了，威曼
Now, Wilmer.
你的计划完全行不通，我们不要再说了
Your plan is not at all satisfactory, sir. Let's not say anything more about it.
好吧，那我有另一个建议
All right. I've got another suggestion.
也许没有第一个好，至少聊胜于无
It may not be as good as the first, but it's better than nothing.
- 你要不要听？- 当然要听
-You want to hear it? -Most assuredly.
把开罗交给警方
Give them Cairo.
天哪，先生…
Well, by gad, sir.
假如我们把你或奥夏克尼希小姐交给警方如何？
Suppose we give them you or Miss O'Shaughnessy? How about that?
你要老鹰，我有老鹰
You want the falcon. I've got it.
替罪羊是我要求的代价 至于奥夏克尼希小姐
The fall guy's part of the price I'm asking.
如果你们认为她可以充当替罪羊 我愿意加以考虑
As for Miss O'Shaughnessy, if you think she can be rigged for the part......I'm willingto discuss it with you.
你似乎忘记了你根本没有资格讨价还价
You seem to forget that you are not in a position at all to insist upon anything.
现在，先生们
Now, come, gentlemen.
让我们基于友善的态度讨论
Let's keep our discussion on a friendly basis.
开罗先生说得有一定道理
There certainly is something in what Mr. Cairo said.
如果你们杀了我，你们怎么拿到鸟？
If you kill me, how are you gonna get the bird?
如果我知道你们不敢杀我
If I know you can't kill me,
你们要怎么吓唬我给你们？
how are you going to scare me into giving it to you?
除了杀人与威胁之外 还有其他说服人的方法
Sir, there are other means of persuasion besides killing and threatening to kill.
是的…
SPADE: Yes, that's....
此话说得没错
That's true.
但是，如果没有死亡威胁一切都不管用
But they're none of them any good unless the threat of death is behind them.
你明白我意思吗？
You see what I mean?
如果你轻举妄动，就必须杀了我
If you start something, I'll make it a matter of your having to kill me,
或算了吧
or call it off.
这种态度需要双方非常谨慎的判断
That's an attitude, sir, that calls for the most delicate judgment on both sides.
因为在白热化中
Because, as you know, in the heat of action...
人们往往会忘记最好的做法
...men are likely to forget where their best interests lie...
而被情绪所左右
...and let their emotions carry them away.
那我这方要做的就是跟你牢牢
Then the trick from my angle is to make my play strong enough...
拴在一条线上 别激怒你，让你失去理智
...to tie you up, but not make you mad enough to bump me off...
宰了我
-...against your better judgment.
天，先生，你真是个人物
-By gad, sir, you are a character.
大只佬，他们要出卖你了
Six-two uneven. They're selling you out, sonny.
我希望你不会顾忌…
I hope you're not letting yourself be influenced by the guns...
这些袖珍版亡命徒挥舞的手枪
...these pocket-edition desperadoes are waving around.
我练过从他们身上取走武器
Because I've practiced taking guns away from these boys before...
一点也不会困难
...so we'll have no trouble there.
- 我们的威曼将是…- 好了！
-Wilmer here is-- -All right.
威曼！威曼！
Wilmer. Wilmer!
Wilmer!
威曼！
Wilmer.
我们有了替罪羊
There's our fall guy.
现在就答应我，否则我就要把老鹰与你们都交给警方
Either you'll say yes, or I'll turn the falcon and the whole lot of you in.
这样不好，先生
Don't like that, sir.
你不喜欢，是吗？
You won't like it. Well?
你可以把他交给警方
You can have him.
要等到天亮以后我才能拿到老鹰，或者稍后
I won't be able to get the falcon till daylight, or maybe later.
我想到为了大家好 最好彼此都不离开对方视线
It strikes me it'd be best if we did not get out of each other's sight...
等到交易完成，你有那个信封吗？
...until our business has been transacted. You have the envelope?
在奥夏克尼希小姐手上 没事，抓紧喽
Miss O'Shaughnessy has it. Hang on to it.
我们不用看不到对方 那玩意儿会送被到这里的
We don't have to lose sight of each other. The dingus'll be brought here.
好极了
Excellent, sir, excellent.
作为1万元与威曼的交换
And in exchange for the 10,000 and Wilmer...
你给我们老鹰和1、2个小时的宽限
...you'll give us the falcon and an hour or two of grace.
我们先谈清楚细节
Let's get the details fixed, first.
他为什么要杀德斯派以及在哪里杀死的耶哥船长？
Why did he shoot Thursby and why, where and how did he shoot Captain Jacoby?
我必须知道详情
I've got to know all that happened, so I can be sure...
才能掩饰好不符合的细节
-...the parts that don't fit are covered up.
我会坦诚相告，先生
-I shall be candid with you, sir.
德斯派是奥夏克尼希小姐的帮手
Thursby was Miss O'Shaughnessy's ally.
我们认为那样做掉他
We believed that disposing of him...
就会使她摒弃异见与我们合作
...would cause Miss O'Shaughnessy to stop and think that it would be best...
解决老鹰的问题
...to patch up her differences with us regarding the falcon.
你们没有试图跟他谈生意就先宰了他？
You didn't try to make a deal with him before giving him the works?
我们当然试图说服他
We did. Yes, sir. We most certainly did.
当晚我亲自与他谈话，但他油盐不进
I talked to him myself that very night, but I could do nothing with him.
他对奥夏克尼希小姐忠心耿耿
He was quite determinedly loyal to Miss O'Shaughnessy.
于是威曼就跟踪他，解决了他
So Wilmer followed him back to the hotel and did what he did.
这听起来不错
That sounds all right.
现在轮到耶哥
Now Jacoby.
耶哥船长会死 全是奥夏克尼希小姐的过错
Captain Jacoby's death was entirely Miss O'Shaughnessy's fault.
告诉我事情经过
SPADE: Tell me what happened.
如你所猜测的，开罗先生
Cairo, as you must have surmised, got in touch with me...
昨天离开警局后就来找我
...after he left police headquarters yesterday night.
他明白共同合作的好处
He recognized the mutual advantage of pooling forces.
开罗先生的判断力很好
Mr. Cairo is a man of nice judgment.
鸽子号是他想出来的 他读到船进港的消息
The Paloma was his thought. He saw the notice of its arrival in the papers...
想起他在香港听说的事
...and remembered he had heard in Hong Kong...
耶哥与奥夏克尼希小姐碰过头
...that Jacoby and Miss O'Shaughnessy were seen together.
他看到那消息
Well, sir, he saw that notice and,
便想出了整个内幕
putting two and two together, guessed the truth.
她把鸟交给耶哥，叫他带来这里
She had given the bird to Jacoby to bring here for her.
在那个关头，你决定迷昏我
And at that juncture, you decided to slip me a Mickey?
我们完全不需要你
There was no place for you in our plan, sir.
我们决定不使自己陷入窘境
So we decided to spare ourselves any possible embarrassment.
开罗、威曼与我联络了耶哥船长
Mr. Cairo and Wilmer and I went to call on Captain Jacoby.
我们抵达时正好碰上奥夏克尼希小姐
We were lucky enough to arrive while Miss O'Shaughnessy was there.
会谈十分不顺利，但我们终于说服了她
In many ways, the conference was difficult, but we finally persuaded...
接受我们的条件，至少我们这么认为
...Miss O'Shaughnessy to come to terms, or so we thought.
我们下了船，准备回旅馆
We then left the boat and set out for my hotel...
我准备要付钱给奥夏克尼希小姐买下那只老鹰
...where I was to pay Miss O'Shaughnessy and receive the bird.
我们应该更聪明些
Well, sir, we mere men should have known better.
在路上，她与耶哥船长还有老鹰
En route, she, Captain Jacoby and the falcon...
从我们指缝中逃脱
...slipped completely through our fingers.
干得很俐落，真的
It was neatly done, sir. Indeed, it was.
你们在离开之前就烧了船？
You touched off the boat before you left?
不是故意的
No, not intentionally.
但我们必须承认，我们至少是威曼要为火灾负责
Though, I daresay, we, or Wilmer at least, were responsible for the fire.
我们在船上会谈时，威曼出去
While the rest of us were talking in the cabin, Wilmer went about the boat...
寻找老鹰
...trying to find the falcon.
显然他对火柴很不小心
No doubt, he was careless with matches.
那枪击呢？
How about the shooting?
我们在奥夏克尼希小姐公寓里追上她与耶哥
We caught up with Miss O'Shaughnessy and Jacoby at her apartment.
我叫威曼守着防火梯 }然后才去按门铃
I sent Wilmer downstairs to cover the fire escape before ringing the bell.
当她透过门问我们是什么人时
And, sure enough, while she was asking us who we were through the door...
我们在告诉她时 听到一扇窗户被打开
...and we were telling her, we heard a window go up.
威曼在耶哥爬下防火梯时射杀了他
Wilmer shot Jacoby as he was coming down the fire escape...
开了几枪，但耶哥非常健壮 没有丢掉老鹰
...shot him more than once, but Jacoby was too tough to fall or drop the falcon.
他爬下去，撞倒威曼逃走了
He climbed down the rest of the way, knocked Wilmer over and ran off.
我们“说服”了奥夏克尼希小姐
We persuaded-- That is the word, sir. We persuaded Miss O'Shaughnessy...
告诉我们耶哥会带老鹰去何处
...to tell us where she had told Captain Jacoby to take the falcon.
然后又“说服”她打电话引你出来
And we further persuaded her to phone your office...
趁耶哥还没有找到你引开你
...in an attempt to draw you away before Jacoby got there...
但我们不走运
...but, unfortunately for us...
“说服”她用了太长时间
...it had taken us too long to persuade Miss O'Shaughnessy.
你抢先拿到了老鹰
And you had the falcon before we could reach you.
威曼，很抱歉要失去你，但我要你知道
Wilmer, I'm sorry indeed to lose you, but I want you to know...
我把你视为己出
...I couldn't be fonder of you if you were my own son.
如果失去一个儿子，总还可以再生一个
But, well, if you lose a son, it's possible to get another.
但世上只有一只马耳他之鹰
There's only one Maltese Falcon.
人还年青时，不会了解这种事情
When you're young, you simply don't understand these things.
要不要来点咖啡？煮点水，天使
How about some coffee? Put the pot on, will you, angel?
我不想撇下我们的客人
I don't like to leave our guests.
当然
O'SHAUGHNESSY: Surely. -Just a moment, my dear.
等等，把信封留下不是更好吗？
Hadn't you better leave the envelope in here?
你担心没有了，干脆坐上面得了
Sit on it, if you're afraid of losing it.
你误会了，根本不是那么回事
You misunderstand me. It's not that at all.
但做生意就必须遵守生意的规矩
But business should be transacted in a businesslike manner.
譬如说，现在这里只有九张钞票
For instance, there are only nine bills here now.
当我交给你时本来是十张，你很清楚
There were 10 when I handed them to you, as you very well know.
怎样？
Well?
怎么回事？
I want to know about this.
你摸走了一张
You palmed it.
- 我摸走了一张？- 是的
-I palmed it? -Yes.
你是想认了，还是要搜身？
Do you want to stand for a frisk?
你承认了吧，要不我要搜身了 没有第三条路
You're going to admit it, or I'm gonna search you. There's no third way.
我相信你会，我真的相信
I believe you would. I do.
你是个人物，如果你不介意我这么说
You are a character, if you don't mind my saying so.
你偷摸了一张
You palmed it.
是的，先生，我承认
Yes, sir, that I did.
我必须时不时开个小玩笑
I must have my little joke now and then.
我很好奇在这种情况下你会有什么反应
I was curious to know what you would do in a situation of this sort.
你成功地通过考验
I must say you passed the test with flying colors.
如果是威曼这年纪的人这么干还说得过去
It's the sort of thing I'd expect from somebody Wilmer's age.
这钱很快就是你的了，收下吧
This will soon be yours. You might as well take it.
我那份应该超过1万元
I ought to have more than 10,000.
这是头期，稍后还有
You understand this is the first payment. Later.
稍后你会给我1百万
Oh, yes. Later you'll give me millions,
现在给我1万5，如何？
but how's about 15,000 now?
坦白说，我用我名誉担保
Frankly and candidly, upon my word of honor as a gentleman...
目前我只能凑到1万元，不能再多了
... 10,000 is all the money I can raise.
但你没有说“绝对不能”
But you didn't say positively.
绝对不能
Positively.
我想给你一些忠告
I'd like to give you a word of advice.
请讲
-Go ahead.
你要给她一些钱
-I daresay you're going to give her money...
但如果你给她的钱没有如她所期待的一样多
...but if you don't give her as much as she thinks she ought to have...
我的忠告是“要小心”
...my word of advice is be careful.
有危险？
Dangerous?
非常危险
Very.
- 咖啡煮得如何，天使？- 几分钟就好
-How's the coffee coming, angel? O'SHAUGHNESSY: In a few minutes.
天快亮了，史派特先生
It's almost daylight, Mr. Spade.
你能不能现在去拿？
Can you start getting it now?
我想可以
I guess so.
喂？
Hello?
喂，亲爱的，很抱歉大清早吵醒你
Hello, precious. I'm sorry to get you up so early.
现在仔细听我，是这么回事
Now, listen carefully. Here's the plot.
在我们邮局的信箱中有一个信封上面有我的笔迹
In the holland box at the post office there's an envelope with my scrawl.
里面有一个寄物箱的收据 可以拿到我们昨天收到的包裹
In that envelope, there's a parcel-room check for the bundle we got yesterday.
立刻把那个包裹拿到饭店这里
Uh-huh. Now, get that bundle and bring it here, pdq.
好女孩，动身吧，再见
That's a good girl. Now hustle. Goodbye.
谢谢你，抱歉破坏了你的休假日
Thanks, lady. Sorry to spoil your day of rest.
你也不是第一次破坏了 还有什么事吗？
Not the first one you've spoiled. Anything else?
- 没有，谢谢 - 那就再见了
-No. No, thanks. -Bye-bye, then.
交给你了
SPADE:There you are.
经过了17年…
Now, after 17 years....
就是它了
It is it.
但我们要确定
But we'll make sure.
是假的！
Fake.
假货！铅做的
It's a phony. It's lead.
铅做的
It's lead.
这是假的！
It's a fake.
你的玩笑开够了吗？说话啊！
You've had your little joke. Now, tell us about it.
不，山姆
No, Sam. No.
这就是我从卡马多夫那里得到的，我发誓
That's the one I got from Kemidov. I swear it.
你…
You.
是你搞砸的！
It's you who bungled it.
你的笨计划！
You and your stupid attempt to buy it.
卡马多夫发现了它的价值
Kemidov found out how valuable it was.
难怪我们这么容易偷到它
No wonder we had such an easy time stealing it.
你这个白痴！
You imbecile.
胖笨瓜
You bloated idiot.
你这个猪头，你…
You stupid fathead, you.
不错，是俄国人搞的鬼，毫无疑问
Yes, it's the Russian's hand. There's no doubt about it.
你有什么建议？
Well, sir, what do you suggest?
我们可以在这里哭泣或互相叫骂
We shed tears and call each other names...
我们也可以去伊斯坦布尔
...or shall we go to Istanbul?
你要去吗？
Are you going?
我花了17年找这玩意
Seventeen years I've wanted that little item and have been trying to get it.
如果必须再花一年时间追寻
If we must spend another year on the quest...
也不过是百上加斤罢了
...well, sir, it will be an additional expenditure in time...
只占个5.57%
...of only five and fifteen-seventeenths percent.
我要跟你去
I'm going with you.
威曼？
Wilmer.
好大一群贼啊
[SPADE LAUGHS] A swell lot of thieves.
你没什么好得意的 先生，还没到山穷水尽
GUTMAN: We've little to boast about, but the world hasn't come to an end...
只不过是小小挫败
...just because we've run into a setback.
- 我必须索回那笔钱 - 我达成了我的协议，你拿到了那玩意
-I must ask you for that envelope. -I held up my end. You got your dingus.
你自己运气不好 不是我的，这不是你想要的
It's your hard luck it wasn't what you wanted.
先生，我们都失败了
Now, come, sir, we've all failed...
你不能要我们负担全部损失
...and there's no reason for expecting any of us to bear the whole brunt.
简而言之，请把1万元还给我
In short, sir, I must ask you for my 10,000.
这算是偿付我的时间与精神
This'll take care of my time and expenses.
现在让我们道别
Now, sir, we'll say goodbye to you...
除非你想跟我们去伊斯坦布尔
...unless you care to undertake the Istanbul expedition with us.
你不去？
You don't?
我倒希望你能同行
Well, frankly, sir, I'd like to have you along.
你是个足智多谋的角色
You're a man of nice judgment and many resources.
既然没得选择了
Now that there's no alternative...
我想你能够应付警察的 不需要替罪羊
...I daresay you'll manage without a fall guy.
我会没事的
-I'll make out all right. -Well, sir, the shortest farewells are best.
道别不需冗长，拜拜
Adieu.
你也是，奥夏克尼希小姐 那件珍品就留给你
And to you, Miss O'Shaughnessy, I leave the rara avis on the table there...
作为纪念好了
...as a little memento.
喂，柏郝斯警探在吗？
Hello. Is Sergeant Polhaus there?
请找他听电话我是山姆?史派特
Yeah. Put him on. This is Sam Spade.
听好，我有情报要告诉你
Hello. Tom? Now, listen. I've got something for you. Here it is.
一个叫威曼的小子杀了耶哥与德斯派
Jacoby and Thursby were killed by a kid named Wilmer Cook.
他年约20，1米68，穿灰色大衣
Yeah. He's about 20 years old, 5'6", wearing a gray overcoat.
他替一个叫顾德曼的工作
He's working for a man named Kasper Gutman.
他重达136公斤，很好认
Now, you can't miss Gutman. He must weigh 300 pounds.
开罗也跟他们在一起
That fellow Cairo's in with him too.
他们刚离开亚力山卓旅馆
They just left for the Alexandria Hotel.
你得快行动，他们想要溜出城外
You'll have to move fast. They're blowing town.
要小心那个威曼
Watch yourself when you go up against the kid.
就这样
Yes, that's right. Very.
祝你好运
Now, good luck, Tom.
他们一旦被抓，就会供出我们 我们坐在火药桶上
They'll talk, when they're nailed. We're sitting on dynamite.
我们只有几分钟应付警察 告诉我一切，要快
We've only got minutes to get set. Give me all of it.
你第一次来我办公室时 为何想要跟踪德斯派？
When you came to my office, why did you want Thursby shadowed?
我告诉你了，我以为他要背叛我，我想查明
I told you, Sam. I thought he was betraying me.
别说谎！你已经钩住德斯派了
You had Thursby hooked.
你知道的，你想在船长带着赃物来前，干掉德斯派
You wanted to get rid of him before Jacoby came...
这样你就不需要跟他瓜分 你的计划是什么？
...with the loot so you wouldn't have to split it with him. Isn't that so?
我以为如果他知道有人跟着他
I thought if he knew someone was following him
他会被吓走
he'd be frightened into going away.
麦尔斯没有笨到会第一晚就被发现
Miles wasn't clumsy enough to be spotted the first night.
你告诉了德斯派他被人跟踪
You told Thursby he was being followed.
我告诉了他
I told him.
是的，但请相信我，山姆
Yes, but please believe me, Sam.
如果我知道佛洛德会杀麦尔斯 我就不会告诉他
I wouldn't have if I thought Floyd would kill him.
不错，他不会杀麦尔斯，亲爱的
If you thought he wouldn't kill Miles, you were right.
麦尔斯没有什么大脑，但他作为侦探
Miles hadn't many brains, but he'd had too many years as a detective...
经验丰富，不会那样被他跟踪的人逮到
...to be caught by a man he was shadowing
跑到死胡同里 枪都没拔出来，外套还扣着
up a blind alley with his gun on his hip.
他肯定是和你去那里的，亲爱的
But he'd have gone up there with you, angel.
他色迷心窍
He was just dumb enough for that.
他跟着你，流着口水
He'd have looked you up and down, licked his lips
咧着嘴笑
and gone grinning from ear to ear.
你在黑暗中可以靠近他
You could have stood as close to him as you liked...
然后开枪杀了他，用德斯派给你的枪
...and put a hole through him with a gun you got from Thursby.
别，山姆，别那样说！
-Don't, Sam.
闭嘴！警察随时就到！说啊！
-The police'll be here any minute, now talk.
你为什么指控我…
-Why do you accuse me?
现在没时间扮纯情女学生了！
-This isn't the time for that act.
我们两个都岌岌可危
We're both of us sitting under the gallows.
你为什么要杀麦尔斯？
Now, why did you shoot Miles?
我本来不想
I didn't mean to at first, really, I didn't.
但当我后来发现德斯派没那么容易害怕
But when I found out that Floyd couldn't be frightened....
看着你我实在说不出来，山姆
I can't look at you and tell you this, Sam.
你以为德斯派会擒住麦尔斯 他们有一人会被干掉
You thought Thursby would tackle Miles and one would go down.
如果德斯派死了，你就摆脱他了
If Thursby was killed, you were rid of him.
如果是麦尔斯 你就会设局让德斯派被逮住
If it was Miles, you'd see Thursby set up for it.
- 对吗？- 差不多吧
-Something like that.
结果德斯派没有攻击他
-When Thursby wasn't going to...
所以你就借了他的枪自己下手，对不对？
...you borrowed his gun and did it yourself.
当你听说德斯派被杀后 你知道顾德曼来了
When you heard Thursby was shot, you knew Gutman was in town.
你需要另一个保护者
You needed somebody
顶替德斯派的人，所以就回来找我
to fill Thursby's boots, so you came back to me.
是的！甜心，不仅是如此
Yes. Oh, sweetheart, it wasn't only that.
我迟早都会来找你的
I'd have come back to you, sooner or later.
当我第一次见到你，我就知道…
From the very first instant I saw you, I knew.
如果你运气好，20年后就会出狱
Well, if you get a good break, you'll be out of Tehachapi in 20 years...
那时候就可以来找我
...and you can come back to me then.
我希望他们不会吊死你 爱的，那么美的脖子
I hope they don't hang you, precious, by that sweet neck.
- 你不会…- 是的，亲爱的，我要把你交出去
-You're not.... -Yes, angel, I'm gonna send you over.
也许会被判无期徒刑
The chances are you'll get off with life.
如果行为良好，20年就可以出来
That means, if you're a good girl, you'll be out in 20 years.
我会等待你的
I'll be waiting for you.
如果他们吊死你，我就永远怀念你
If they hang you, I'll always remember you.
不要这么说
Don't, Sam.
别这样说，哪怕是玩笑
Don't say that, even in fun.
我有一刻被吓住了，我以为…
I was frightened for a minute. I really thought....
你真的会做这种最野最难以预料的事
You do such wild and unpredictable things.
别傻了
Now, don't be silly.
你要去俯首认罪
You're taking the fall.
你一直在玩弄我
You've been playing with me.
假装你关心这样设计我
Just pretending you cared to trap me like this.
你一点也不关心
You didn't care at all.
你不爱我！
You don't love me.
我才不上你的当！
I won't play the sap for you.
不是这样的，你不能这么说
It's not like that. You can't say that.
自从我认识你
You never played square with me
你一刻都没有对我诚实过
since I've known you.
你内心很清楚我爱你 尽管我做了这些事
You know deep in your heart that in spite of anything I've done, I love you.
我不管谁爱谁！我不会上你的当！
I don't care who loves who. I won't play the sap.
我不会步上德斯派的后尘 我不知道还有多少前车之鉴！
I won't walk in Thursby's and I don't know how many others' footsteps.
你杀了麦尔斯，所以你要为此负责
You killed Miles, and you're going over for it.
你怎么可以这样对我，山姆？
How can you do this to me, Sam?
当然，麦尔斯不会比我还要…
Surely Mr. Archer wasn't as much to you as....
听着
Listen.
这样是没有用的
This won't do any good.
你永远不会了解我 但我要试一次，然后就不会再试了
You'll never understand me, but I'll try once and then give it up.
当一个人的拍档遇害 就必须要设法做点事情
When a man's partner is killed, he's supposed to do something.
不管你对那个人有什么评价
Doesn't make any difference what you thought of him.
他是你的搭档，你该为此做些事情
He was your partner, and you're supposed to do something about it.
这是私家侦探这行的规矩
And it happens we're in the detective business.
如果伙伴被人杀害
Well, when one of your organization gets killed, it's....
就不应该轻易放过凶手
It's bad business to let the killer get away with it.
这对所有私家侦探都不好
Bad all around, bad for every detective everywhere.
你不会指望我相信这就是
You don't expect me to think these things...
送我给警方的充足理由吧？
-...are sufficient reason for sending me--
让我说完，然后你再说
-Wait till I'm through. Then you can talk.
我没有理由信任你
I've no earthly reason to think I can trust you.
如果我们这次能逃过 我就有把柄在你手中
If I do this and get away with it, you'll have something on me...
你就可以随时利用我
...that you can use whenever you want to.
既然我也有你的把柄
Since I've got something on you...
有一天也许你也会赏我一颗子弹
...I couldn't be sure that you wouldn't put a hole in me someday.
这些问题全是事情的一面
All those are on one side.
也许有些并不重要，我不会去争论
Maybe some of them are unimportant. I won't argue about that.
但看看有多少问题？
But look at the number of them.
而事情的另一面呢？
And what have we got on the other side?
我们有的，也许是你爱我 也许是我爱你
All we've got is that maybe you love me and maybe I love you.
你知道你是否爱我
You know whether you love me or not.
也许我爱你，把你交出后，我会有几天睡不好觉，但一切都会过去
Maybe I do. I'll have some rotten nights after I've sent you over, but that'll pass.
如果我说的一切都没意义
If all I've said doesn't mean anything to you
就忘了一切，我们就这样
then forget it and we'll make it just this.
我不会，因为我全心想要罔顾后果
I won't because all of me wants to regardless of consequences.
因为你依赖我
You counted on that with me the same
就像你依赖其他人一样
as you counted on that with all the others.
如果老鹰是真的，你拿到钱了 你会这样对我吗？
Would you have done this if the falcon had been real and you'd got your money?
不要认为我真的那么坏
Don't be too sure I'm as crooked as I'm supposed to be.
恶名昭彰也许能带来好生意
That sort of reputation might be good business...
带来高价位的生意和敌人打交道更容易
...bringing high-priced jobs and making it easier to deal with the enemy...
更多钱当然是另一件事 比较对你有利
...but a lot more money would have been one more item on your side of the scales.
如果你爱我，就不需要更多理由
If you'd loved me, you wouldn't have needed any more on that side.
请进
Come in.
嗨，汤姆，逮到他们了吗？
Hello, Tom. Got them?
逮到了
POLHAUS: Got them. -Swell.
好极了，这里还有一个，她杀了麦尔斯
Here's another one for you. She killed Miles.
我还有一些证据，小子的枪，开罗的
Oh, and I've got some exhibits. The boys' guns, one of Cairo's...
想要贿赂我的1千元
...and a $1,000 bill I was supposed to be bribed with.
还有那个黑雕像，一切都是因它而起
And this black statuette here that all the fuss was about.
你的同伴怎么了？
What's the matter with your playmate?
看起来心碎了
He looks brokenhearted.
我打赌他听到顾德曼的故事后 以为逮住我了
I bet when he heard Gutman's story, he thought he had me.
别说了，山姆
Cut it out, Sam.
我们走吧，回去局子
Well, shall we be getting down to the hall?
真重
It's heavy.
这是什么？
What is it?
这是人类梦想的原料
The stuff that dreams are made of.